Hello. Welcome to my talk about building a web UI for the Fedora installer. So my name
is Martin Coleman, and I work in the team that's building the Anaconda installer used
by Fedora, REL, CentOS, and REL distributions. First, I would like to talk a bit about, like,
why we decided to actually build a web UI for our installer. And, yeah, first, like,
very, very shortly about, like, the Fedora installer project. Yeah, the name of it is
Anaconda, which is very confusing for some people doing Python in the scientific domain,
because there is a very similar project in that it's like a Python thing, but it's called
the same SV, but I think we are older. So, anyway, right now we have a GTK3 UI for the
installer. We have a text-based UI. It's also possible to fully automate the installation.
We have things like add-on support, and, yeah, we are used, as I mentioned, by Fedora, REL,
CentOS, and others. This talk is basically concerning only the graphical user interface.
We don't expect to have any changes for the text-based interface and the kickstart-based
automation in the context of the web UI. So, why did we actually choose to do something
about the current graphical interface, and why did we choose to start working on a web
UI? So, one of the points is that the current GTK interface comes from the year 2013. It
kind of looks like early GNOME 3 by coincidence. Maybe it was built at the same time, basically.
And over time, we added new features. We fixed bugs. We adapted to various Fedora changes,
for example. And the stuff kind of got bolted on. Like, not always it was possible to change
the UI. So, in some cases, it's getting a bit clunky already. Another issue is that
some of the technology we built it on is getting a bit old right now. GTK 3 is not that old
at the moment, but already you have GTK 4. Eventually, we would have to port it. One
of the issues is, for example, that the Fedora installation image. The Fedora project tries
to have minimal dependencies of applications. So, like, over time, we want to have, like,
the minimal amount of libraries. So, we would have to quite possibly migrate to keep the
image sizes small. That's one of the reasons. We also still run on top of X. There is even
some hard dependency right now on keyboard switching during the installation. So, this
is something we would have to address anyway. The remote access to a graphical installation
right now is not the best. It's based on VNC. So, it's unsecure. It's not very efficient.
It requires you to have a graphical system running on the host that you are installing.
And you need a special application that might not be available that users might need to
install. So, that's one of the issues. And also, I'm not saying it's not possible to
test GTK 3 interfaces, but basically, it's not that simple. And we don't really have
any unit test coverage. Like, there are people from, for example, the Fedora QA community
that do test Anaconda. But what they are using is basically a screenshot or graphical bitmap
based testing right now. So, this is something that could be improved. And also, what we
have seen in the past years is that there seems to be a clear trend towards using Web
UIs for system management. Some of you might still remember some of the system config tools
used on Fedora and CentOS and Trell that used to be available to configure stuff like services,
networking, firewalls. All of these, over time, effectively became cockpit plugins for
the cockpit web console. So, this seems to be the trend overall for system management
as far as we can tell. So, what we kind of found out, there are some benefits of doing
something about the current UI situation and doing something about it with a web technology
based UI. So, while we are at it, we can address some of the UX issues we have right now because
it's effectively a fresh start right now. It's easier to achieve a consistency because,
yeah, you are building the whole thing. So, you can make sure that it's, since it feels
similar, it's using the same concepts, the same workflows for everything, hopefully.
Also another thing is that given the proliferation of Web UIs everywhere, basically, there seems
to be much bigger community of users, of developers of these technologies. And there is overall
more documentation, there is even more resources for non-developer roles like UX designers
or usability testing projects. And this seems to be, unfortunately, quite lacking in many
native GUI libraries right now in comparison to the web technologies. And also, like one
quite big point for it is that using a Web UI, just to be specific, we are going to use
the Web UI both locally and remotely. So, we want to run it for the local graphical
session, if any, but also it makes it much, much easier to access the installation remotely.
So, for any headless installations, it should be much easier for the users using the installer
to connect securely and much more efficiently to the host that is being installed. Also,
the host doesn't have to contain any graphical dependencies, effectively, because all the
rendering is happening on the client. So, the installation image could be much smaller.
And also, the installation time resource requirements could be much, much smaller. That could be
an issue for stuff like Raspberry Pis or some IoT SBCs, which are perfectly fine for the
tasks you will be using them. But if you try to do a graphical installation on them, varying
like possible issues with drivers, it might need much more resources to just install,
to bring up the graphical interface, then it will be using for its lifetime of doing
some useful work. So, let's talk a bit about the technical
details of the tools that we are using to build the UI for the third-line installer
right now. So, this is the overall architecture. The install is already modular. In that,
it has a Python backend, which has a D-Bus interface. Then we are using Cockpit to provide
us a bridge between D-Bus and the web application, which itself is then written with ReactJS
for the logic and PatternFly for the web UI widgets. The current Anaconda with the GTK
3UI with the text UI, and even with the Kickstart support, is actually using the same Python
backend, and even the GTK 3UI already is communicating with the backend via D-Bus. So, this makes
it possible for us to right now work in parallel, that we are building the web UI next to these
other UI's right now. Just instead of, like, directly calling D-Bus, you have PatternFly
widgets React talking via D-Bus, calling D-Bus calls from the backend. This is very similar
to Cockpit plugins in general. Usually, you have the networking screen in Cockpit, for
example, and what it does, it's talking to network manager via this bridge. It's doing
D-Bus calls from D-Bus. That's basically the idea of Cockpit, and we are reusing this for
our project. Yeah, so, as I've already mentioned, it's not about another UI that you can remotely
access while keeping the current graphical interface next to this. Like, eventually,
once we cover all the necessary functionality for the given project or product, it should
replace the current graphical interface. But right now, it's being developed next to
it, and thanks to the module backend, thanks to the D-Bus interface, it's not that hard
to do it. Also, one more thing that we found very, very useful is the Cockpit test framework.
This is addressing the issue I've mentioned previously about no unit tests for the graphical
interface. This is something that has been developed for the Cockpit project itself,
which directly maintains a lot of the screens you will see when you install Fedora or CentOS
or some such distribution and enable Cockpit. But there are also many community maintained
outside of the main community developing Cockpit, many other Cockpit plugins. So, that is very
comprehensive and I would say very nice test suite, which makes it possible to essentially
write Python unit tests that then manipulate your web UI or Cockpit plugin, in our case,
the Anaconda Fedora installer web interface. And it also supports pixel testing, which
we are thinking, yeah, this is nice. But then we actually thought about the other issue
that most web applications have and that's dependencies. There are dependencies being
pulled from NPM for pattern fly, for React.js, and the other libraries you might need to
use. And the problem with this is that the release cadence is pretty fast. There are
new versions of pattern fly all the time. And it would be very easy to get left behind
basically to have very big difference in using some old version and being much harder to
upgrade later on. And pixel tests make it much, much more easy to update this automatically
or almost automatically because you can effectively compare if you see any graphical changes from
the old to the new version. Same thing for any changes for the web UI. You can easily
see what the new state looks like if you see some changes that are expected, if you change
some label or add a button, or if the layout is totally wrong. So, yeah, this is something
I can recommend for web applications. It seems to be very, not something we expected
to be using, but it helps a lot. And it's a part of the cockpit test tooling. So, okay,
so how far we got? This all started about a year ago in earnest. And right now we have
a very simple but end-to-end installer images that can be used to demonstrate the web UI.
And actually, you will end up with a functional, minimal but functional system. It's possible
to select an installation language. We already support geolocation like with the current
GTK3 interface. It's possible to select disks. It's possible to dynamically add disks. Again,
this is kind of a demonstration of some dynamic behavior we wanted to have there. That's it
right now for storage. Storage, I'll talk a bit more about it later on. But that's one
of our main focus points because that's like 90% of everything in store. We have a review
screen where you can see the settings. And where you are also told that, yeah, you shouldn't
really run it right now on any production system that has any useful data because you
select the disks and we will use them. We will wipe them and use them. So that's the
minimal storage we have been able to come up with for now until we have some more comprehensive
screen where you can actually keep partitions and stuff like that. And the last one is just
a progress screen where you can see the installation happening, where you can see some errors if
there are any, where you can kind of guess how long it will take because that's not always
easy to tell the user correctly. So to have at least some pictures in the presentation,
so this is in general how it looks like. If you've seen the current Anaconda, this is
quite a departure from it. We decided to have flexible result layout. And if you've seen
some pattern fly applications, this should look pretty familiar. And that's one of the
aims as well, like people who use cockpit or some other applications using this tool
kit could be quite more familiar than seeing some a bit outdated GTK3 interface in some
unfamiliar theming. So as you can see, it's pretty similar. This is the installation destination
screen. We already have some built-in help support. You can click on some of the information
links. You will get a doc with help content. This is demonstrating just some simple disk
selection. You can plug in an USB drive already to add more disks. We expect this to grow
in functionality quite a lot for stuff like network attached storage and more complex
disk layouts. And this is the review screen. Right now it looks very similar, but again
we expect this to grow quite a bit because as we add more screens, this should directly
proliferate here. And we are looking into ways how to, for example, visualize more complex
storage layouts because that will be challenging, but it was one of the pain points we got from
users so far. Yeah, this is the progress screen. This is basically the last thing you will
see. Then it will just tell you, yeah, you are done. So that's it, like four screens
right now. But it's already producing functional systems. One other outcome of this project
so far is preview image. Sorry for the long links, but essentially the main information
here, if you go to Fedora Magazine and type in Anaconda, you will get a bunch of articles
about the WebUI because that's what we are writing about Anaconda right now. So there
is a preview image. The idea is that we will refresh it once every time we add something
visible. Right now it's about like a month old, but I would expect some new features
landing in the next few weeks. So this will be updated regularly. And that's the best
you can use right now to have a feel of how the WebUI looks like. It's a self-contained
image that effectively dumps F37 user space into the machine that you run it on, and please
don't run it on anything production resembling. So we found some challenges like working on
this. We have a huge amount of functionality. The project is all the current UI has been
used for like nine years. So we are really trying to kind of check what is being used
and what not. So we don't go insane implementing it all. So that's ongoing. We try to identify
and avoid some of the UX problems we have right now. Also, and keeping things consistent.
Like that's one nice thing about Pattenfly. There are pretty nice UX guidelines that
you can apply on many, many things. And that helps to keep the UI consistent. Yeah, another
issue is how to run this locally. That's not that easy, actually, because the web engines
are pretty monolithic, pretty big. And they come with some mainly RAM requirements, not
to mention the image size requirements. And there are actually not that many usable web
engines on federal. It's effectively a GDK WebKit or Firefox. And each one of them has
some pluses, some minuses. So right now we are still comparing these two and deciding
which one to use. For remote running, that's kind of not our problem that much. Even that's
another issue with Pattenfly. Like if we see some corruption, some layout issues, it quite
possibly would affect other Pattenfly users. And you might not need to do something about
it unless, unlike if we used some very, very custom web UI stuff. For the remote running,
another issue is how you actually authenticate the thing, how you encrypt in a useful manner.
So this is still ongoing, how we solve that. It might not be pretty, but one way is to
show some certificate fingerprints to the user to show some generated passwords or stuff
like that. Another option is to use custom images. That might be perfect for some cases
to bother some for others. So we will see right now. The web UI image you can use right
now is, this is disabled right now. But if you use the inst.wepoi.remote option, you
can actually access the web UI remotely. But you need to pass it because it's like totally
unsecured right now. These mechanisms are not yet in place. So okay, this is really
in planning stages and we don't have much time to talk about it. But the main focus
is definitely storage. This will be big. We plan to have something that you can manually
do, something that guides you. And so, yeah, it should start landing in the next few preview
image releases, definitely. And yeah, more screens, definitely. The priority is driven
by the next, the first image we could reply to, basically. So right now there is like
some date and time work already running. We have some backups for user and through password
configuration, we need to add the error reporting, definitely, and other stuff. It definitely
add-ons. Already the UI supports them. We need to keep it. And yeah, I think this is
actually, yeah. So this is, uh-huh. So this is the, this is the effect of the last slide.
And it's, I think we can start with the questions just quickly. Like, storage is a big focus.
This is a way you can provide feedback to us about it. And let's start with the questions.
Thanks.
Hey, Martin. I don't have a question per se. Oh, yeah. Right. Say, I really appreciate
the stuff that you folks are doing. I tried doing this myself by wrapping kick-start with
ViewJS, Flask. And I thought that it would be really feasible, really easy thing to do.
But when I started implementing it, I came to know the kind of entry cases that I was
to take care of. So I'm totally looking forward to what you folks end up doing. All the best.
Thanks.
Okay. Oh, Anaconda has now just nice features as escaping to a terminal, for instance, to
bypass things Anaconda can't do at the moment. Do you retain that too? What plan do you do?
So the current text interface, as well as, like, if you can access the machine locally,
it should still be possible to do, like, anything in the terminal that you can do today. And
you should be also able to use the existing text interface. We won't be changing that.
Yes. But you can escape the web interface and get a terminal? Or what is the way to do
that?
This is not, like, yet settled, like, if you will include it. But the cockpit project
has built in terminal emulated. I could imagine this to be included in the web UI. So we might
be able to include it in our web UI, as well.
Would be nice if you did.
Yes. Thanks for the feedback.
Thank you for the talk. I think this is very interesting. And I think it's a good idea.
And, you know, certainly convenient to set up headless machines this way. But at the
same time, I was wondering, I think it was Alex Larson who wrote this Broadway back end
for GTK. So basically you could use GTK and it would output to what goes into a web browser.
And I, you know, it just comes to my mind, why not use something like that instead? Because
I think that if you, we want to continue to invest in GTK and technical technologies
using GTK, because we need GTK for Fedora, we don't really need web for sure. And so
if we can end up using GTK and investing more resources there, maybe this makes it just
overall better for the whole health of the ecosystem. And we get our web UI, too.
So thank you.
Yeah. I must say I don't have, like, really, like, very recent information about it. But
we looked at it a while ago, basically, to the, at the Broadway technology. It definitely
looked interesting, but it didn't, it looked more like a Tehdemo back then. It could have
progressed since then. But I think there have been some issues, like with authentication
or possibly performance. So, yeah. That's a good point, but I don't have, like, latest
information right now for it.
I would check.
Okay.
I mean, then you can have all your, you can have the GTK and you have your web, everyone
with one code base.
Thank you.
Well, that's another question. Before Fedora's 37, we had a discussion about soft rate installation
using the BIOS boot machines and we found a good solution. But Anna Kodna is currently
a bit strange installing software rate on e-fi systems because we don't use an e-fi system
partition but a rate partition. Do we have a chance to get that fixed, too?
I'm not sure. Like, I, like, I, it's not that many people actually in the installer team
and have been very much concerned and concentrated on the, on the web UI right now for the couple,
last couple months. But definitely if you reach out to us, like, we have a mailing list
or we have a metrics channel, I think, right now already for Fedora. So please reach out
using some of these channels and we can look at it.
Yes. Oh, we can do that.
Absolutely. Is it, is it possible to provision the machine from the cockpit because you can
already create in cockpit virtual machines? So it would be nice to be integrated in one
place in one console. Is it possible or do you have such plan?
I think it's a, I don't think we have, like, integration for it right now. But that's an
interesting idea and, like, we have been thinking for stuff like satellite and some other provisioning
mechanisms that it would make sense to more closely integrate with the installer, with
the web UI because you could avoid the certificate and authentication issues if you could, for
example, inject something into the image. So that could, that could work. Like, you could
have, like, create machine or provision, bare metal, whatever. And it could, like, include
some, like, trust chain anchors, whatever, into the installation run. And then you could
then directly connect to the machine. Yeah, we have been thinking about it. But we haven't
yet implemented something like this. But it seems like obvious choice for some mechanisms.
And yeah, with integrating it like this with cockpit machines, that could be a nice idea.
So thanks for the suggestion. Okay, thanks. Okay. Thanks a lot.