Good morning, wow.
I was not expecting this much of an audience at 9am on Sunday at a FOSSTEM, so thank you
all for coming.
Yeah, I'm here to talk about how I was at FOSSTEM five years ago.
I told you all a whole bunch of things, and I was utterly wrong.
So many ways, it's actually kind of amusing.
But who am I?
My name's Richard.
I've been working on OpenSUSA since it began.
I've been a customer of SUSAs, I've been a contributor, a bit of everything, Q&A engineer.
I've been working there for 10 years now, or almost 10 years.
These days I am a ridiculous advocate of rolling releases.
It's what everybody should be using.
I created the micro-S desktop.
My day job is being one of the release engineers for Tumbleweed and micro-OS.
I also do a bit of consulting, and I also do a bit of photography.
But a long time ago, in a room actually just on the other side of this campus, I was here
at FOSSTEM telling everybody that containerized applications, so things like flat-back, snap
app images, the idea that graphical apps in some portable format are absolutely utterly
terrible and nobody should be ever using them ever, and they were going to eat all
of our users, and yeah, it's just going to be horribly, horribly wrong.
I even started the presentation with quickie comments, like those who don't remember the
past that condemned to repeat it, and I even made really unflattering comparisons.
Doing diagrams from Windows architecture and pointing out Windows has all these wonderful
run times where you can have different environments and run your application on top, and it was
absolutely terrible in Windows.
It's going to be absolutely terrible when we do the same thing in Linux, giving the
examples of all of the security issues that you see in Windows in this kind of approach.
Things like security-relevant DLLs lurking in some folder in your Windows machine, being
an absolute nightmare to patch, an absolute nightmare to fix when it goes wrong.
All these horrible update issues, how do you end up getting an update on your Windows or
your Mac machine?
Well, you download some EXE or some bundle and then there's some updater in it, does
whatever the heck it wants on its machine.
Licensing issues, especially with open source, how do you mix and match all these different
licenses together in one cohesive thing?
It's just going to eat up all of your disk space.
Then I went back to this slide again and then started talking about the various technologies
at the time, 2017, were out there doing this containerized runtime stuff, and I would compare
this lovely Windows diagram to this lovely canonical diagram, which looks very, very
similar because, actually, it is.
The idea is similar, the concept is similar, but as you'll see, just because the concept
is similar doesn't necessarily mean the whole idea is bad, execution doesn't matter.
And it wasn't just Snap, I wasn't just shifting on Ubuntu because I don't like Ubuntu, I was
doing the same with Flatback.
And I was basically pointing out that this whole containerized application idea was repeating
the same issue.
We were going to be going down this road of security relevant libraries, lurking in all
of these snaps in Flatbacks.
Back then, we didn't necessarily have a good story about how are we going to update these
things, how are we going to keep them maintained, who was going to look after all of these base
snaps and run times in Flatback and the like, who was going to look at all of the legal
issues and review the possible licensing issues of bundling these things together, and who
was going to buy everybody bigger hard disks.
And the kind of main conclusion that I left with, which despite the fact you'll see I
was wrong about a lot of what I said, I still actually hold true, is at the heart of it,
when distributing software, doesn't matter if you're doing it as a container or as a
full-blown fat OS distributor or anything in between with any kind of fancy technology,
the responsibilities are the same.
App image, Flatback, Snap might make it easier to be the upstream than giving out your application
to the users, that's great, but the responsibilities are still the same that distributors have
been doing in distributions for years.
You have to worry about maintainability, you have to worry about the security, you have
to worry about licensing and all this wonderful stuff, so they're going to have to borrow all
of the same stuff.
So five years ago I gave this presentation, there was lots of people in the audience from
App Image, Snap and Flatback, some of them said very nice things to me, some of them
said very un-nice things to me.
Starting with App Image, they took a lot of what I said surprisingly on board and really
ran with it.
I said all this stuff in February 2017 and by June 2017 I was saying stuff like this
on stage, this was taken at the OpenSUSA conference, this was on the App Image website
for longer than I wish it was.
But the reason it was because in that short window, App Image is thought they could address
most of my concerns by actually obviously running to the OpenSUSA build service and
working with the OpenSUSA build service guys and integrating App Image really quite nicely
with it at the time.
So the idea being the App Image wasn't the problem, maybe the way you build App Image
is the problem.
If you build them in a nice auditing build system and have the whole thing tracked with
dependencies in a build system and you build it reproducibly and you do all the licensing
reviews there, then OBS could be the solution to all of the App Image's problem.
And they worked really nicely with it and they gave all these promises, they'd be encouraging
people to be using OBS as the main App Image building tool and we'd all move on happy in
a nice unified way forward.
And I even said things to Snappy and Flatback like you're falling behind App Image at this
point, saying App Image had a better build story and they were working with other people
and telling people to be more like App Image.
And I still was badgering on, by the way you can tell all my old slides because they have
this thing at the bottom so you can see old me compared to new me.
I was still worrying a little bit about dependencies because as you'll see App Image makes some
really interesting assumptions.
But I was in June 2017 kind of hopeful that we'd get to a point where everybody would
be working together and we'd have sort of maybe a new consistent run time and things
could move forward.
I was also hopeful that we might have sandboxing finally because Snapp kind of had some with
App Armor, Flatback has Bubblewrap, maybe App Armor would be the way forward.
How wrong I was.
So now five years later, where are we?
And I don't want to go deep down in technical issues too much because a lot of this isn't
just technical, we're an open source project, any technical issue can be fixed, right?
It is a lot about what are people actually doing, what do they actually care about, where
are they actually taking things, what are we actually doing?
So let's judge people by their own standards.
This is a screenshot from the current App Image website and it says use this to make
Linux apps that run everywhere.
But they don't run everywhere.
And they say as a user it should be as easy to install as it is on a Mac or Windows machine.
But they're not.
And they say you don't have to learn all these distributions with all these different distros
doing things different ways.
Technically that's true.
You just need to learn all these different distributions and doing all the different things
and you have to build your own to put in your App Image.
And I'm not just saying this to core shade on them.
I have users on microOS who are trying to run App Images.
And they can't because App Images require Fuse 2.
I'm a rolling release.
I haven't shipped Fuse 2 for like a year.
I've been using Fuse 3 and you can't get an App Image to work with Fuse 3.
It has to be Fuse 2.
The portable image format that isn't portable because it makes assumptions about stuff that's
on the base OS.
And not just weird stuff like Fuse but even down and dirty in the kernel.
If you're running Debian and you're trying on an electron app it's not going to work
properly because the kernel in Debian isn't built the way that App Image is expecting
the kernel to be running.
So this is great promise and it's going to work in some places but only if you're lucky
enough that your distro has the same assumptions baked into it that App Image has.
And this is a recurring issue even reading the app image documentation for building App
Images.
It tells you as a developer think about all of the distros where you want your app image
to run on.
So the whole promise of not worrying about distros goes away.
You have to worry about more of them than you normally would and put every single dependency
which might not be fulfilled by that distro in your App Image.
So yeah, avoid distros by building a huge one and putting it in a big table.
It's a lot of work.
It's way too much work.
I utterly respect anybody using it because they're probably doing more work than I am
doing a rolling release.
Really when the recommendations for what you put in that giant App Image is the oldest
crustiest stuff you can find.
They recommend avoiding using anything new because anything new is more likely to have
compatibility issues with older distros.
So literally find the oldest distro that's still supported and use that as your base
for building App Image.
Which also seems a bit of a problem to me because if you're always picking the oldest,
the oldest is always the first one to not get maintenance updates.
So you're always going to be rebasing on some crusty old almost out of day LTS to do what
you want to do with App Image.
It doesn't make any sense by their own standards.
And they tell everybody that it's installing just like on a Mac.
Just download the binary, put it on your desktop, right click it, make it executable and it'll
run, which 15 years ago, that's true, that's how you run something on a Mac.
I own a Mac now.
That's not how you run stuff on a Mac.
There's not a single Mac application I've ever installed that works that way.
Even the Apple documentation makes it very, very clear that if you're downloading something
from the Internet and you're double clicking it on a Mac, it's going to run an installer,
which is a terrible thing anyway.
But it needs to run an installer.
When you're downloading random stuff from the Internet, it needs to be checks for dependencies.
There needs to be some modification to what's on the host.
So every random downloaded Mac application has an installer, just like Windows, or it's
done in an App Store where Apple are controlling all that kind of things and helping that along.
So yes, I was wrong about App Image, first thing it was terrible because they did try
and make an effort.
But then I was wrong again because it's actually even worse than I said five years ago.
They failed to do everything that they set out to do.
They don't do anything to address the actual problems with software releasing.
Dependency problems are just hand-waved worse than anyone else could possibly do.
Licensing issues, security, maintenance, good luck.
Just build a new distro and ship it again.
This is worse than we do in distros with all of the faults I will admit distros have on
this.
So please do not use App Images.
And also they're not nice people because they kept publishing this for four years after
I told them to take it down and I had to threaten to sue them.
So they're just not nice.
Now Snap, despite my reservations back in 2017, actually Snap was at the time the one
I was most optimistic about, you know, at the time Canonical were actively collaborating
with other distributions.
They even invited me to a Snap workshop trying to get Snap supported in as many Linux distributions
as possible.
They had an approach of upstream first.
They were promising that all of their app armor patches and all of the enablement they
had to do was going to end up in the kernel and going to end up being upstream.
At the time in 2017 you could run your own Snap store so you could have your own repository
for downloading Snaps.
And unlike Flatpak where it's much more just graphical, they also had a story for non-graphical
apps.
It's only five years ago but back then everybody wasn't necessarily using containers for server
stuff the way we are now.
So it was interesting on all those levels.
But it's five years later.
And all of the promises of Snap confinement working everywhere so you can have your nice
sandboxed Snap application hasn't come true.
Snap D does not support confinement on most non-Obuntu distributions and even some Ubuntu
distributions.
And this was posted on their forums three years ago now.
That was the case three years ago.
I was still waiting to get any kind of proper sandboxing insecurity with Snaps.
Still not there.
And then this was posted this month.
Still promising.
It might happen.
But it's been five years.
None of the app armor stuff is in the kernel yet.
None of the enablement we need is in the kernel yet.
Distros can't easily or really at all keep with an upstream kernel and get Snap running
in the way Snap should be running.
So if you run a Snap on a non-Obuntu distribution, you're probably running it in an incredibly
insecure way.
Do you trust that random software delivery with access to everything on your machine?
Probably not.
At least that random software developer using Snap isn't using their own Snap store because
they can't anymore.
In 2017 you could, then they released a new version of SnapD.
So now the only version of the Snap store that works with SnapD is Canonicals.
So it's an open source package format, but it's a closed source delivery format.
You're only going to get that software from Canonical.
And if you read up on it, there's lots of examples where Canonical have done the right
thing and handled Snaps that were malicious and got them off quickly.
But it's like, how do you know?
You're just trusting Canonical that they're always doing the right thing because you can't
see.
You can't see what they're putting on there.
You can't see how they get there.
You can't do it yourself.
If you trust Canonical, that's fine, but I'm much more open source orientated myself.
Even if I am trusting somebody else, I'd rather be able to have a look and see what's going
on in there.
Maybe run my own, maybe compare something alongside.
And yes, for most developers, or at least most small developers, this is free.
So you can build your Snap and publish it to the Canonical Snap store with no effort.
But as soon as you start getting bigger, as soon as you start becoming a bit of an ISV
or doing stuff with IoT with lots of devices, then Canonical want you to have a brand store.
And this isn't a documentation for Snapcraft where it comes to building.
When you actually have a look at the price list for having a Snap store, the price list
is kind of dear.
Do you really want to be spending at least 5,000 euros just to be able to publish your
application on somebody else's server under your name?
But I can understand if people are buying into this.
I can definitely understand why Canonical aren't in a rush to change it.
It's probably making them a good bit of money.
Canon OpenSuser, like I said, at the time in 2017, they were working with us.
Now, not going so well.
Snap is the only bit of software in all of my years doing anything, police, managerial,
OpenSuser, where it's felt more than one security order.
It's the only bit of software where I've had to project it multiple times.
And there was good collaboration going on to get those issues fixed.
But since 2019, that's kind of fizzled out.
Haven't seen anything since.
So when it comes to Snap, I was wrong.
I was really kind of keen on Snap back in 2017.
And these days, I can't really say that much nice about it.
The upstream first promises have all stored.
It doesn't seem to be an effort to get it really moving again on other distributions.
So it's not a portable format by any stretch of any imagination.
There's no open source delivery option, even if the Snap store may always be the best way
of doing it anyway.
This is a case to be made for that, even if there was an open source way.
And it's not really a viable alternative for something like Flatback until unless you use
Ubuntu, unless you trust Canonical, and unless you're willing to give them money to distribute
your stuff.
And so Flatback.
Now I need to kind of do a little bit of a detour on this, because when I was talking
five years ago about all of this stuff, one of the things that I was trying to pitch in
the side thing there was this idea that, well, everybody should be using rolling releases.
I really, really believe that, and I still believe that now.
And I really think in this modern age, to get applications in the hands of users, a
rolling base operating system is the absolute key.
You need to have it all built together, need to have everything integrated, built consistently,
tested consistently, and taking the fair share of the maintenance and security burden, and
then shipping it all in a way that the users don't really care that everything's churning
around underneath, you know, it just works.
And at SUSE, we've still been working on this.
We have an operating system called Open SUSE MicroOS.
Vanilla MicroOS is much more server-orientated.
It's immutable, like CoreOS and other similar immutable platforms.
Can't be modified during runtime at all.
It's rolling, so changing snapshots, it's actually using the same code base as Tumbleweed, so
every day, almost.
It's small, but small enough to do the job that it's meant to do.
And the assumption is, you know, that server is going to do just one job in a data center,
so, you know, a VM running one RPM or a VM running containers, and then, you know, as
many containers on top, but, you know, the job is a container from the operating system
point of view.
And this is working really, really quite well.
In fact, SUSE also has commercial products based on this, Slea Micro is based directly
off Open SUSE MicroOS.
The new SUSE Alp you might have heard of, where we're thinking of doing, like, a whole
new ecosystem of enterprise distros, you know, that's building off what we did with Slea
Micro and Open SUSE MicroOS.
But me, you know, I'm still a desktop guy.
So, you know, doing this with my day job, I found myself asking, yeah, I found myself
asking, okay, so I've got this nice small OS, and it can run just one thing, you know,
what if that just one thing was a desktop?
And so, I started the MicroS desktop project, sort of alongside regular MicroS.
And yeah, basically, it's a modern Chromebook-like, silver-blue-like environment where you have
a nice minimal base system.
My recommendation would be running the GNOME one, that's the one that's most maintained
with the desktop environment on top.
And the basic configuration tools are, yeah, the in there, but everything else is provided
by somewhere else.
In fact, everything else is provided by Flatpak.
So this is one of the reasons why I'm doing this presentation.
I kind of have to explain how in five years I went from Flatpak is the devil to Flatpak
is the only thing you should be running on your desktop.
Because I talked to some of the people that I was talking to back then, and this is kind
of their expression.
Because five years ago, when I was talking about this stuff, I was meanest about Flatpak
than all the other ones.
I was even invited to Gwadek, and I gave the meanest talk I have ever given to anybody
right to the people who were actually developing the thing.
And the guys from GNOME, they listened.
I wasn't right, I'm not right about everything, that's the recurring theme of this presentation.
But they challenged my opinions, but they accepted at least the cool ones that actually
mattered, and Flatpak has changed.
Like I was talking about earlier, responsibility is the key issue when you're talking about
delivering software, no matter how you're distributing it.
You need to be thinking about dependencies and licenses and maintenance and security,
and one thing that Flatpak does very, very well is basically take all of that away from
the distribution and make it the packages problem.
Not great if you're a package, but they do it in a way that actually probably lowers
the burden for everybody, so that's nice, automation and technology is great.
But really, dependencies become the issue of the person making the Flatpak, licenses
become the issue there, maintenance, security, et cetera.
So distros can stop worrying about it.
And Flatpak does this very well with their runtime concept, where if you're building
an application for GNOME, you have a GNOME runtime, if you're building an application
for KDE, you have a KDE runtime, elementary have their runtime as well, and then for everything
else there's the generic free desktop runtime, which is a little bit heavier and clunkier,
but gets the job done.
And back in 2017, this terrified me.
Not because there was competing distributions, because I'm used to competing distributions.
The question was really, are these mini-distributions going to be maintained, anything like every
other distro out there?
Are these going to handle CVEs well?
Are they going to not have horrific licensing issues, et cetera, et cetera?
Well, they've been doing this for five years now.
These runtimes are very well maintained.
These snapshots from their various git trees, they're all updating very, very quickly, keeping
up with their respected upstreams of GTK and QT and what have you.
Handling CVEs very, very well, I don't know more about that later.
So basically, they're handling this just as well as any other distribution does, maybe
even better in some cases, because they're narrow in scope, they've actually got less
work to do themselves than a full-blown distribution with tens of thousands of packages.
So you've got your runtimes, and you've got your Flatpak application on top of that, but
what about the Flatpak client, especially if you think about what I was just talking
about with Snap earlier, with all of the issues with app armor and custom patches and what
have you.
Well, as a distribution guy, getting Flatpak in my distribution is really not that hard
at all.
You need to have the client on that, but you're not having to worry about a huge chain of
dependencies and a whole bunch of plumbing to get it running.
I don't need to have Fuse2 on my distro.
All I need to have is bubble wrap, OS3, and a couple of XTG packages, and they themselves
don't really pull that much in as well.
So it's small, it's simple, it's relatively easy, self-contained.
Doesn't cause me huge build chains when I have to rebuild the whole thing in tumbleweed.
It's a really nice ecosystem to just plop on top of my distro and then all of the applications
come from Flatpak.
From a licensing perspective, all the Flatpaks on FlatHub are checked.
They all have to have some kind of license that allows open redistribution or legal redistribution,
or they do also support proprietary stuff.
You can get a Spotify Flatpak.
But obviously, you can't have the source code for the Spotify binary in their Git tree.
So all of the proprietary stuff has to be pulled through by discrete declared links.
And the Flatpak, specifically the FlatHub team, are checking that, verifying that things
aren't changing there, not letting nasty things happen and binaries flip around.
So at the very least, you may not know exactly what horrible thing is in this sandbox, but
it's sandboxed.
It's not much of a threat to your machine anyway, and it's the one that was sent at
the submission time.
You know it was the one that was reviewed.
You know it isn't changing unexpectedly.
So basically, it's as good or as better as any other distribution out there with their
native packages.
When it comes to maintenance, basically the same story.
Just like OpenSuser, FlatHub doesn't like Flatpaks to have distro-specific packages.
They want everything upstream as possible.
They have an incredibly robust build, test, publish workflow.
They're not using OBS, I wish there was.
They're not using OpenQA, I wish there were.
But what they're using is just as good, maybe in some ways it's better.
They can actually give everyone nice test channels for testing their application, which
I really think I want to copy sometime.
But yeah, it's maintained.
It's easy for maintainers to keep their app maintained, and that is all ticking over nicely.
From a security point of view, well, Flatpak is the only one that works everywhere.
It's the only one that those applications are sandboxed.
The portal concept where basically holes are pegged through the sandbox to give you things
like access to the file picker and other parts of the file system and the like has proven
to be secure enough and expandable enough.
It's not great.
It's not perfect.
Nothing ever is.
But it's doing the job, and it's doing the job well, and these applications are working
very well, and Flatpak CVEs happen very, very rarely.
When they do happen, they're not these terrifying, scary things, because the thing is architected
very, very well.
The last CVE that I could find was in February 2022.
It was a medium score.
It was fixed incredibly quickly.
I think every distribution had no problem adding that, because again, like I mentioned earlier,
given the client is very well structured, you don't have a huge dependency chain.
Even the most ancient of OTSS distros can then just happily get the patch in, get the
thing running.
When I started the microS desktop, I adopted Flatpak, actually November 2017, so if you
put the timeline in that, I did change my opinion quite a bit from the beginning of
February 2017 to the end, but I was using Flatpak as it was the one that I could work
with.
I couldn't use Snap.
I couldn't use App Image.
I didn't trust it that much at the time.
I was thinking like you've seen with other distributions of building my own Flatpaks
and using them rather than trusting FlatHub, or doing like Fedora does with, they build
their own and then they also give FlatHub with some kind of filtering, but I didn't
really want to mess with that at the beginning of my project doing all of this, so I just
opted for trusting FlatHub first, and then waiting for the problems to surface.
It's five years later, and I'm still waiting.
We haven't had a single issue with the microS desktop where a FlatHub application really
got in the way and needed us to think, okay, we can't trust these guys, we should start
doing what I want.
It just hasn't happened.
The few times an application hasn't worked right, well, we send a patch.
We work with them, because that's how open source is meant to work.
As a distribution guy, I've realized we don't need to be building these giant, humongous,
huge code bases, even though that's still what we do with Tumbleweed, I don't meet myself.
I'm purely a microS person now.
All of my servers are microS.
My desktop here is microS.
I'm using a tiny 1,000 package fraction of my Tumbleweed code base, and everything else
is coming from containers, some of which are built from that much bigger code base.
All my graphical stuff is coming from FlatHub, and my life is good, and I'm happy.
This presentation is Libre Office from FlatHub.
My final thoughts, which I've realized I've actually finished them a little bit early,
but that's good, more time for Q&A.
FlatPacks are ready for prime time.
The other ones aren't.
Don't use app image, only use Snap if you trust Canonical, but we're here at FOSTEM.
FlatPacks are the better way to go for people like you who are here at FOSTEM.
My system automatically updated in the background.
Desktop Linux distros do not need to package the whole world.
If you're a distro builder, think about following the model we are doing with microS desktop.
Think about, if not narrowing your scope because you're building the packages and you don't
want to tell maintainers to go away, then at least start drawing your focus more on just
what you need to be doing.
Start testing that part more.
Start telling your users, that's the bit you can really, really trust.
Give some secondary class to the old fashioned way of doing things.
Yes.
So you are telling us that FlatPacks run everywhere.
Is that also true for different architectures?
That is true at least for ARM, for Z probably not, but do you really have that many desktops
in the main frame?
Yes, of course.
Well, then that's something I'm sure the FlatHop team wouldn't mind, I'm sure we could
get that working on FlatPack, like if there's a need there, then also thinking about a risk
drive of course and stuff like that.
But then that kind of point, actually nicely draws me to my sort of finishing point really.
None of this stuff is ever going to be perfect.
No technology ever is.
That's why we do this stuff in the open.
That's why we do this stuff open source.
So when things aren't perfect and aren't the way they are, aren't covering a architecture
that you want or whatever, isn't it better to go to a project that is already going in
that direction, that is trying to be available to everybody, that is open to me yelling at
them for months about how terrible they are and then work with them to get it all done
rather than sticking in your own tiny little sandbox, doing it all on your own and then
being burdened with it for decades.
If you're doing graphical applications, this is the way we should be going.
It's easier for package maintainers, it's easier for distros, it's easier for everyone
to keep up, it's easier for users too.
I mean, you just, you know, nice little web store, they click on what they want, you know,
they can have the beta version if they publish in the beta version, it's a nice way of getting
stuff done.
So yeah, please, if you're doing anything with graphical apps, please get it on FlatHop,
please contribute to FlatHop, please put FlatHop in your distro.
And is there any other questions, because, yes, right at the back there.
You've addressed the outstanding question about CPU architecture, which is a great question.
How do you feel about the fact, and I realize I'm asking a Linux question of a Linux distro
maintainer, but how do you feel about the fact that containers tie everyone in the world
to the Linux kernel interface as their interface, shutting out other open kernel options like
the BSDs from participating in that ecosystem, and that the overall drive towards containers
is further orphaning these already minimally represented, but very, very strong options
in other kernels?
They're strong, but I mean, I guess the recurring point I get to with all of this kind of thing
is, you know, niche players are great for playing in niches, you know, when you're talking
about something that needs to have widespread adoption and or widespread contribution, you
know, some degree of centralization does make sense.
It doesn't make sense for everybody to go make their own kernel, it doesn't make sense
for everybody to make their own distribution, I would say it doesn't make sense for everybody
to go packaging their own graphical applications 20 times over, so as hard as it is to say
to somebody who's clearly passionate about other kernels and BSDs and what have you,
I'm fine with containerization and these technologies dragging everybody to the Linux kernel because
that's where the contributions are, so, you know, and as long as the Linux kernel is open
to contributions and everybody can steer it in, you know, a good direction, I'm kind
of okay with that.
Thank you for your talk.
I was with the presentation of 2017, so I think it's very nice that you changed the
views.
That year I also watched a presentation about Atomic from Fedora, so it was funny how those
things interlept.
I have a question about how you feel about the base system.
You see currently there are trends like NICs and like SteamOS which use like an immutable
image as a base.
How do you feel about that?
So I think immutable distributions are the way to go.
Like I think if you're running Linux, it should be immutable.
Immutability does bring with it a bunch of extra questions and, you know, and for us
as geeks, I think I can say that without insulting anybody in the room, you know, we are keen
to tinker with our machines and, of course, immutability quite often can get in the way
of that.
You know, if you can't change your running system, how are you going to install that
one little thing that you want?
I think there's a sweet spot and I don't think some of the other distributions get it.
You know, imaged-based deployments, you know, you've got a frozen image, you can't really
modify that image or you have to build a whole new one.
That's too much work.
I don't like imaged-based immutable systems that much.
NICs has an interesting way with everything being declarative, but it's a lot of hassle.
Declaring everything, it kind of swings the other way for me.
So I don't necessarily like the NICs way.
OS Tree has, you know, an interesting take on the whole thing where, you know, both from
a user's perspective and the fact it's immutable, like, it's nice, but then you end up with
a million different layers of OS Tree and that kind of just gets technically burdensome.
Obviously, I work on micro-OS.
I think we found that sweet spot.
You know, in our case, we're using BTFS snapshots to do all the magic underneath the hood where,
you know, your running system never gets touched, but you can still do traditional package management
against a new snapshot and that becomes your next boot target.
So you never affect in the running system, but you can do whatever the heck you want
with your next boot and then if that next boot goes horribly wrong, we just throw the
whole snapshot away.
So, you know, it's super fast, super easy, avoids all of that.
You can still tinker with it, but you're not, yeah, unfortunately, the downside of that
is I do sometimes have to tell people, like, don't tinker too much, like, the more you
do crazy stuff, the more likely you're going to throw that snapshot away, but I think that
sweet spot is better than super lockdown images or, like, complete freedom of having to declare
everything in conflict for.
Okay, thank you for your presentation.
I had never heard of Flatpak.
On my Ubuntu, I'm using a Snap to install application and on my Mac, I'm using Homebrew.
What do you think of Homebrew on Linux?
I don't see the point of Homebrew on Linux.
Yeah, it's, yeah, why, like, I get it on Mac, I've installed a few things on my Mac
that I desperately need there, but, you know, my Mac, I use for photography, I don't do
anything technical on it, so, yeah, I, yeah, don't see the point.
Okay, thank you.
How likely is it for the files stored in the home directory, especially the user files,
to be affected if I roll back a snapshot after a failed upgrade?
So, yeah, that's a really, like, micro-specific question, that's cool, though.
The way we do it on micro-OS is when we talk about the root file system, we're not talking
about the root partition because we're using BTIFS.
So BTIFS, you have this concept of sub-volumes, we have a sub-volume for literally everything
where the data should be changing, so Homeopt because that's third party, so it's not us,
you know, use a local because, again, that's not us.
You know, anything that isn't the distro is in a sub-volume, and then the distro's root
file system is just that last bit that's left.
So that bit's read-only, that's the bit that's managed by the package manager, all the sub-volumes
are freely available and read-write.
That doesn't make ETC a little bit interesting because that's like the one folder where it's
both, like, distro's put stuff in there, and that, in micro-OS we handle that with
overlayFS right now, where, yeah, we're basically taking copies of that, having, knowing what
we put there, knowing what the user put there, or at least trying to, and then merging everything
together so the thing works.
Ideally, what we would like is everybody to start using, like most people already are,
user for putting in distribution configs at USR, you know, it should be, you know, in
userlib or useretc or whatever, that's just like you see with systemd, right, where distros
put their distroconfig in userlib systemd, and then users put their localconfig in ETC
systemd, and that way works very, very nicely.
But meanwhile, ETC's a bit of a mess, but a mess that we can manage.
Thank you for the presentation.
Why isn't FlatBag suitable for CLIs?
Actually, it is suitable for CLIs.
It's actually guides now for how to do that.
I think the, so yeah, I know our examples of apps where they do that, where, you know,
the assumption is always probably going to be that it's graphical, but there's no reason
why a graphical application, you know, can't start an exterm and run a CLI app.
So there's actually examples in the FlatBag documentation of how to do that.
Maybe speaking though, like sort of, you know, for apps that, you know, might not fit that
kind of model, I think a lot of that kind of CLI or more sort of service-based command
line-y stuff, that's handled so well by OCI containers, you know, Podman, Docker and the
like.
Like, why mess with that?
Like, you know, you've got all those containers already out there.
You've got everyone building the, you know, command line tooling and server tooling in,
you know, in containers, you know, that does very, very well in that context.
It just sucks on the desktop.
Have FlatBag that just handles the desktop issue.
You don't necessarily have to have one thing to do everything.
So yeah, I think FlatBag draws that line quite nicely, where it just, it naturally starts
getting painful when you head down that road.
Any more questions?
No?
Well, hopefully I will see you in a couple of years when I'm long again.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.