Okay. So, hello. Let me introduce us. Like you may have heard, we are from Red Hat, from
Bruno, actually, and we are going to talk about DNF, DNF5, a new generation as we have
in the title. To introduce us and the talk, we have it split into three sections. The
first one is covered by me. It will be a technical overview. Then there is a community history
and action items by Nicola. And finally, a live demo from Jan. First, I would like to
explain what are we actually talking about. I imagine you must have already noticed, but
DNF is a package manager. Probably the easiest way to explain this to someone is to compare
it to, like, an app store or command line app store. So, it installs, upgrades, removes
packages and dependencies, and stuff like that. And there are many examples. You might
be, and we are actually working on DNF and micro-DNF. To put this into some more context,
we have this diagram that's actually describing Fedora. But I think many distributions have
something, some similar setup like this. You can see that it's possible to interact with
the package manager on, like, many ways or in many levels. But here we are talking about
the high-level manager, and that is DNF or LibDNF. If we focus on that section, we could
see a diagram of components that, for the current version, looks something like this.
There are some problems with this, actually. And at first glance, I think it already looks
more complicated than it needs to be. But mainly, you can see that the LibDNF, the library,
is split into two sections. And DNF is actually just using the Hawkeye section, but not the
Libheave one, while micro-DNF is using both. This would be fine if there was some extra
functionality in micro-DNF, but it is actually the other way around. Micro-DNF does less
than DNF, and this is because we have, like, duplicate code there. That's, of course, not
good, so we should fix that. And the other big issues is with the extensions or plugins.
Most of our plugins are for DNF, and they are in Python, but as you can see from the
diagram, it's not possible to use the same extensions in micro-DNF. There's, like, simply
no way how to get to them. And also, the other way around, if you have some extension for
Libheave, it doesn't get used in DNF. This is, again, not good, because we already have
some extensions that we want in both, and we have to duplicate them. Again, like, that's
just a bad situation. And to resolve that, we are introducing or creating DNF5. I should
mention that when I say DNF5 here, I mean, like, this whole part of the stack, so the
library, the plugins, the actual command line DNF tool. But the new diagram looks like this.
It is much simpler. We have merged the insights of the library into one piece, and we have
also merged DNF and micro-DNF into just one tool, which is here called DNF5. There's also
a new DNF demon. We still have to, like, to plug in two nodes here for plugins or extensions,
but it is much more clearly separated. We have, for the library, we have more, like,
a passive extensions that get used automatically. Every time you use the library, they get
loaded and run. And for DNF5, there are some more, like, active plugins. So this is typically,
like, a new command that you can add, and the user actually has to, like, type it and
run it. Okay. Another big two features are that we actually are breaking API, and it's
not backwards-comfortable. So, okay, these are not exactly features, and you might ask,
why are we doing this? So let me try to explain that or justify it. First, for the library,
we completely restructured the API and tried to make it better and most importantly unified
and safer, because before, like I mentioned, it was merged together a bunch of things,
and it wasn't that great. So hopefully, this time, we try to learn from our mistakes and
make it better. And we are, another change we are also doing is inside of the library.
For example, we are now loading and downloading the repositories at the same time. This is
because typically downloading the repositories is network intensive, but loading them on
the other end requires CPU, so they kind of nicely match together and can be done at the
same time. Another change is no, we don't download the file list metadata by default.
If you are not familiar, then the file list metadata contains a list of every file in
all of the RPMs, so it is quite a big file, and we think it's possible to get by without
it as other distributions do, so we don't download it by default, but of course, it's
still possible if the user wants to download it or even configure it, so it's downloaded
every time. Okay, then we are trying to make it, of course, in general faster, and I think
we will see this in the demo later. And, yeah, we have bindings for the new library. We mainly
focus on Python, because that's most of our users, but thanks to Sveak, it should be possible
to generate also for other languages, like Ruby, and it will need some work to do that,
but hopefully it wouldn't be too bad. Now I'm moving to the actual command line package
manager, DNF, DNF5. Probably the biggest change or one of the biggest changes is that
we dropped Python as a dependency, and this is actually what allowed us to merge micro
DNF and DNF together, because before we needed micro DNF for containers on minimal environments
where you need smaller footprints, but since now we don't need Python and everything is
in C++, in C++, we have best of both worlds. Yeah, not everything has changed. Most of
the commands are actually the same, except for a couple of differences that needed, like
picking or fixing, but on the other hand, the outputs of the commands did change. In
fact, we do run still the same CI test that we run for DNF4 as well as for DNF5, and usually
you have to change the checking of the outputs to make it work. Not all of the tests work,
but we are still developing it and working on that. Yeah, then there is the daemon, and
just really quickly, it already is accessible by debas, and since it uses the whole library
or the same library, it will have the same functions, so you can use it to work with
groups or modules and stuff like that. Okay, last thing from me, I want to mention a couple
of additional improvements. I'm not going to match too many details, but we have configurable
aliases, fully integrated modularity, just single configuration for all the users of
the library. We manage to separate system state from history database and module state,
and for example, we have built in autocomplete. There is address, and if you have questions
about this or anything else, you can of course ask us after the presentation. Okay, so that
was everything from me, and let me now hand it over to Nicola and the community part.
Thank you. So after the technical overview, let's focus more on who is actually contributing
to DNF5 and how we are changing our idea of looking at the community, not just our idea
of the code base, how we plan to change our approach with the community. So of course,
DNF5 is an upstream project, so it all starts from upstream, and it was a, I would say quite
a bit chaotic in the past because components were a bit separated, issues were not enabled
for DNF, for example, for quite a while, now they are, but it wasn't super clear the path
we were taking with the community, many issues stayed open for a while, poor requests are
reviewed, we didn't do great, but we plan to change it. So let me give you an overview
of what was the past of DNF contributions, then we will look of what we expect in the
future, and then the action items that the team has to make everything more transparent
and all the workflow much clearer. So first of all, the past of the projects. So I'm saying
projects because here I graphed the weekly contributions by author of DNF, and DNF and
DNF5, and what I want to pull out from this graph is that, well, first of all, now the
effort of the team is all focused on DNF5, as you see, it's just all the contributions
are on the green part, and one other interesting thing is that, yes, DNF5 efforts are higher,
are more, compared to DNF or LibDNF alone, but actually the effort, if you sum, the highest
points of DNF and LibDNF, the efforts of DNF5 is less, and that's because you have
to maintain a unified code base, and that's much, much more easier to do, just one thing.
Also I want to show you during the history of the project how many people actually contributed,
so these are on the Y, the number of people that did some number of contributions on the
X, so there is some exceptional guy, around 200, there is some others, there's just one
guy, 150, 125, and I like, everyone is doing a very small number, so that's fact, and that's
how upstream works, you have exceptional core team members that they will do all the job
and they are carrying, they're pulling the efforts, but it's actually good to maybe improve
the community a bit more, and well to give you maybe some more perspective, you can even
see, like this is, every bar is a contribution, so it's a different person, and yet again
there are just few people that did a huge amount, a huge number of contributions, sorry,
and many, many people that did just a few, like one, which of course are important, but
what it means to us when we, what it means for us having someone from outside contributing,
so I had this idea of kind of splitting the contribution into groups, and here is my analysis,
so there are of course the authors of the project, they are responsible of let's say
the 10% of the total number of commits or contributions, right, and there are one, two, max five maybe
in the project, those are like the key components, they are there from the beginning, I'm talking
generally, but this applies for our components, and there are paid programmers, co-authors,
exceptional contributors that are doing a hundred of commits, a hundred of commits, well
it's quite a number, right, and then of course there are the one-liners, the people that
come and they're like, hey there's a typo here, super important as well, but they are
just, they come and go, you will never see them again, and well they might be not even
interested, sometimes they just come and they are just doing one small fix and going away,
and then there are who I call the people in the middle, so actually the people that can
effectively contribute by following the project and by coming in more than once to just point
out, hey, I am doing this request, maybe I am opening an issue, and then the contributor
get interested in working into the project and does active commit, let's say, so brings
in some code, or maybe deletes some code, deleting code is very important.
So let's look at how we perceive contributions from inside a team.
So for DNF, talking still about weekly contributors, we had a total of 225 contributors for authors,
so four people that did more than 10% of the whole work, and 19 people, very good people
that did 100 commits, and those people, they are regular, they are since forever, you kind
of know that they are there helping you out, but let's focus on the others.
So how many commits are in total, and how many have been without those people, and the number
is actually roughly 10,000 total commits, oh, sorry, I am talking about contributions,
so it's a little bit, so it's smaller numbers, but still, like the statistic applies.
Roughly 4,000 commits without the authors, and roughly 1,000.
So 1,000 commits are done just by those people that stay in the middle, more or less.
And so what is your effort to be, let's say, active member of the community, so I said,
okay, I want to do the 1% of this, that's pretty easy, you do roughly one, sorry, 11
commits, 11 issues, 11 whatever, 11 comments, and you are actually 1%.
If you know 100 people, you definitely remember if one person is missing or not, or like,
hey, you, I don't know, you change your haircut to pink, and you remember because the 1% is
quite a lot, so it's very easy, and I'm talking about 11 contributions in all the history
of DNF, and DNF is being active for like 10 years, so it's like one contribution per
year.
It's quite easy, right?
And now it's the time to jump into DNF 5, because if you look to DNF 5, same applies,
it's basically just team effort, so 5 authors roughly, this number will decrease with time,
and 6 very good contributors, and then those are the number of contributions, and again,
if you do 1 to contributors, we value that kind of contribution, whatever it is, quite
a lot, I mean, it's significant, this is what I'm trying to bring up.
So what kind of contributions are we talking about?
We have a transparent workflow, we have open issues now, we triage all the issues weekly,
this is something that again, we were not doing for DNF for some time, we have public
milestones in GitHub, so you can understand what our action plans are, and also we have
discussions open that we use for announcement, that we use for, yeah, gathering opinions,
like DNF 5 naming is discussed on GitHub, so you can go there and give your opinion,
and questions of course, if you have a question now, you can ask it, if you have a question
later, there will be the link to GitHub to just go there and ask something, and of course
we have bugzilla for Fedora tracking, and I mean, downstream requests or specific Fedora
things, but like, the upstream is where we start, and the upstream is where we are trying
to improve to the community, a bit more to that, we have now a better documentation,
the documentation is actually generated from the code base, it is tested, so everything,
every snippet that's there gets compiled if it's C++, gets interpreted if it's in Python,
and so it's much more, let's say, reliable documentation, so we expect to have, I'm not
saying what we expect to have, you know what, because you'll never know, but then we have
now tutorials, we have code in place, we have a lot more material that Newcomer could work
on and start to contribute to DNF using that material, right, and then we are planning
to also add contributing guides that now are missing, but we are planning to improve the
contribution workflow on GitHub yet again, and also to open first-time issues which are
missing, but we are targeting that, so just to conclude my part, who's the community?
Actually the community for us is the people who create issues, I mean, not create problems,
create GitHub issues, right, people who add or remove code, and people who take part in
the discussions, even now, even just by coming to us and saying, hey, DNF, you know what,
I tried it, it worked, or it broke my system, it happened, so I mean, it can happen, it's
not perfect, or the people who raise questions, like now, or again, they are reaching back
to us to the mailing list, the more questions we have, the more reliable we can provide
a code that actually works for the most user cases, so, and just using DNF, you are part
of the community, and most importantly, and I really feel this quite a lot, because when
I started working on DNF, I actually needed help from the team, and I believe that many
people didn't quite dive into the contribution system, because they didn't have help, so
we are actually in the need of people that help, and ask for help, and that will bring
to all the other points, so, well, I hope now it's much more clear how we intend to
work in the future, and now, let's see how DNF 5 works in practice with the demo, so
here you go, Jan will talk to you about the demo.
Okay, so hopefully it will work, so, okay, let's try some hands-on UCGs, and what do
we have here, so, we have two separate individual containers, both running Federal Unix, and
on the, they have the same configuration, and on the left side, I will show you the
examples using the original DNF command, and on the right side, I will show you the same
examples running the DNF 5 command, so, let's start with something simple, just install
a package, so, we will try to install this package, hopefully the Wi-Fi will work, and
I will try the same on the right side, okay, and now, what's going on, we need to download
the metadata about the packages, so, basically, what are the packages, what are their dependencies,
the requirements, so, the definition of repositories is configured in the system, and now we need
to just pull all the metadata from repositories, and now we can see the first difference between
the DNF and DNF 5, what I was already talking about, and it's the size of the metadata,
because in DNF, everything was hard-coded, and always, all metadata was downloaded,
so there is, like, 64 megabytes for the Fedora 37 repository, and if we look into DNF 5,
there is just 21 megabytes, and it's because of the file lists are not there by default,
because usually we don't need them, okay, we can see some differences in the outputs,
like, for the DNF 5, we have some more information there, like, what packages are being replaced,
yes, but it's basically, it looks very similar, but the output should be a little bit more
convenient for the user, so let's try to install the packages, and, yeah, that's it, basically.
Another example, Alice was talking about the auto-completion, so this was also improved,
we can see that for DNF, there was also some auto-completion, if we try, for example, the
mark command, I will type the M, and now the double-tap, and we can see the DNF offers
the commands for us, okay, that's fine, but the mark command has also the sub-commands,
so if I type the double-tap again, oh, it shows me, like, the installed packages on the system,
so these are the arguments I should use, but if we see the help, like, we need to use one
of those three sub-commands, and these are not suggested by the DNF, so this was improved
for DNF 5, we can look at this, if we put the M and double-tap, we can already see that
there is some difference, there is also some brief description of the sub-commands that
are all the commands that are offered for us, and if we now put the double-tap again,
we can see also the sub-commands there, so, and, of course, there is also the auto-completion
of the option, so we can use the double-tap again, and we can see all the parameters that
are relevant to this command, and it's quite, it could be quite convenient, so now let's
try some performance comparison, so, for example, the repo query command was quite improved,
so it's basically the command for querying the packages based on some keywords, on filtering
it, and so on, but for this example, we will use just the empty repo query, which basically
lists all the available packages in repositories, so let's try that, running also for DNF 5,
and we can see that the DNF 5 was a little bit faster, but let's measure it exactly,
so let's use the time command, and the same for DNF 5, and we can see for DNF it was like
almost three seconds, and for DNF 5 it was one second, so it's a little bit faster there,
and we can also try some more advanced repo query, so we can list all the packages that
depend on CuraLibrary, and we will see that there will be, oh, there should be quite a
big difference, all right, so what depends on, right, so running it, I will try to run
it parallel, and we will see, okay, so here is about six seconds for DNF 5, it's quite
fast, and for DNF it will be like three times longer, I think, okay, twenty seconds, okay,
so that's it from the CLI demo, and we can move to API, and you could ask why I should
introduce the API, well, of course it depends on the use cases, but usually if your project
has like support, one of our scripting languages we have the bindings for, like the Python,
it could be much more convenient to use directly the API, and also it's more powerful than
the CLI interface, but some common use cases are simpler to write through the command line,
and so sometimes in the end the client chooses both approaches, right, okay, so let's see
some simple API example, let's say we have some, our favorite package, and we want to
know what are the latest available version of this package in different federal releases,
could be useful, so let's see step by step what we need to do, so if we have installed
the double packages and the API bindings following our tutorials on the GitHub pages, the importing
of the Python module is super simple, then we need to set up the session for the DNF,
and running some initialization method, then we need to override the release version variable,
which is basically used in the repository URL, so we always look only for the packages
of the respective federal release, then we need to prepare or load the repositories from
the configuration and prepare like the objects for the Python, and then we need to prepare
the query, what we will actually be querying, so this is also quite simple, there is a package
query object, and we will just filter all the packages containing the kernel name, and
we want to have the latest version always, that's simple, and if we found any of those
packages containing kernel, we just print the name of the package, otherwise not available,
okay let's try it, running this simple script, and for federal 35 there is this kernel version,
for federal 36 there will be some probably newer one, it's taking long, and also should
output for federal 37 something a little bit newer, okay, now we can try to edit our script,
and show you if we have already some dnf5 package available, but yeah, we need to add
here a raw height version, a development version of the Fedora, doesn't work, I don't know how
to, does anyone know how to exit V? I couldn't resist, I need to escape, it's a different
laptop, and the thing is that it's actually a different laptop, because the htmi wasn't
working, so I don't know, escape is not working, thank you, if anyone has any questions we
will try to move on, and maybe we can move on, okay so you will never know if dnf5 is
actually in some fedora, well guess what we will say it anyways, but it's always exiting
it, oh maybe I got it, so in federal 35 there is no dnf5, in federal 36 no dnf5, oh maybe
for raw height, no, it's taking some time, I don't know, maybe just, oh it's there, okay,
we can move to some more challenging example, but if we want to add some, our awesome new
command to dnf5, so then the user will install it and just type dnf5, our command and it
will do the magic, it's quite simple, we can show it to write some simple dnf5 plugin in
like 5 minutes, so what do we need, okay we need devil and binding packages, that's no
problem, we can install it following the tutorials, we need some template sources, okay you can
steal our dnf5 plugin sources and use them, and you need some build tools and build script
and you can also steal the cmake script we have for the dnf5 plugin, no problem, everything
is in our dnf5 repository, and now how to write it, you can follow like our structure
of dnf5 plugins, it's basically always some definition file like the header, what's there,
the actual implementation, the cpp file and then there is like the adapter for the plugin
API, but it's like boilerplate code, you just need to change few lines and it will work,
so let's look at this c++ example, there is the implementation of really simple example
command, and it's following like the command interface from the dnf5, so there is some
methods for the setup of the command we need to follow, in this step we need to tell the
dnf5 we have some new command, so we basically register our new command into the dnf5, this
is super simple and it could be copied from other plugins, then there is setting the argument
parser, basically parsing the arguments, what are the arguments for our new command, listing
all the positional arguments and what we have, but in this simple example we don't have any,
so we just set some simple description, in the configure section we can like modify the
dnf5 session, change some configuration or request some optional method that we downloaded,
here we just gonna be quiet, and there is the actual implementation of the command in the
run method where we just, we will just output something on the terminal, and here I will
show briefly the editor code, so this is the boilerplate one, you just copy it and change
a couple of things, this is like the plugin name, the version like name your outer and
name of the plugin, then there is long block of some boilerplate code that is same for
all the plugins, each plugin consists of one or more commands, so we just put our new command
into the list, and finally we need to return the instance of our new plugin class, and
that's it, so let's try to build it and run it, at first I will show you that there is
no, no example command for dnf5 right now, so I'm not cheating, right, and here are the
sources, right, there is the cpp file I was, I was showing, then there is the header file
which is basically just the definition, and the adapter code in the example plugin cpp,
and then there is the build script for the cmake which is, which is stolen from the dnf5
sources, okay, so we just need to create build folder, and then we will do everything to
make it, woo, there is again some weird keyboard, wow, I need, this is not English, I need like
the mperstand, English, no, this one, how to, where is it, there we are, nice, oh, it's,
how did you, what happened, I don't know, this, show me again, what the shift and, oh, it's
printed in Italian, sorry, so make it, make install, so basically just build the sources,
and the installation is just the copying of the library into the correct place where the
dnf looks for it, so building is done, and we can try running dnf5 example, and yes, we
did it, let's see, okay, so when will dnf5 release, you discovered already, dnf5 is actually
already in fedora row height, so 38, and there is a plan to, well, in a moment, so first
of all, if you're running stable fedora 36 or 37, you can use a hopper to try it, and
it will be parallel installation with dnf, and also here are all the sources that we
have for whatever, you can find everything in the github repo, that's the only link you
need, there's everything there, we have all the links copied in the talk information,
if you run fedora row height, or if you're in a container of row height, you want to
try it, it's there, so just dnf install dnf5, and you're good, and something more about
it when it will actually land in fedora, so there is a plan to do a major upgrade of micro
dnf that will actually sim link to dnf5, so it will be replaced in fedora 38, and in
fedora 39, there's the plan to replace dnf with dnf5, so it's coming, and we hope to
be ready for that, that's it, thank you, and if you have questions, you have time, so any
question? Thank you so much for this presentation, my question is related to community, you demonstrated
there is quite a few people that are not making more than like one, two, three, four commits,
can you tell me what is your plan to help people contribute more, how are you going
to improve the contributor experience? Thank you for the question, so the idea is to once
again make it simpler and be more proactive to help people, so again in the past we weren't
very responsive, and people got pissed because their code was just ignored, and their questions
were not as important as maintaining dnf, or that was a perception from the outside,
and now we try to, again, every week we go through all the discussions, all the new issues,
all the new PRs from community, in all our components, and we set an action plan for
that, so we set the milestones in every one of that, it's like we want to make this land
in fedora 38, we want to make this land in fedora 39, so you know what is our priority,
and we take seriously, in serious considerations, PRs, so if you just drop some code, it's very
easy for us to review it and be proactive to that, and once again, it's done weekly
and it's on our priority, our workflow has changed, hope you answered, thank you.
Just a technical curiosity, is the new dnf5demon intended to replace the packagekitdemon?
Is the dnf5demon intended to replace the packagekitdemon?
So it can, we did start with that in mind, because packagekit was officially deprecated
before, so that was one of the goals, but lately I've seen that packagekit is maintained,
and there is even issue on our page that someone wants to create back end for dnf5 for the
new IPI for packagekit, so I'm not sure how it will turn up, but we will see, it was the
plan originally.
So the thing is packagekit works, so it's not that easy to, I'm hearing, okay, well,
I would say that for now gets the job done, but still, there's an alternative, actually
the first enablement of dnfdemon on the system, they will be for other components that are
less critical to probably to adapt to the new dnf, or actually the new IPI, we're looking
at cockpit, for example, that could use the demon, or anaconda maybe could use it, so
it's not just packagekit for which the demon would be relevant, let's say that.
Just finally, we would like to do that because, like to replace it because it could provide,
for example, like I mentioned, the module support, or group support, even to Grom Software,
which is currently not possible, and that would be nice, yeah, so any other questions?
Hello, I do also have a community participation question, are you talking, or have you considered
reaching out to other RPM-based distributions beyond Fedora and the CentOS, like OpenMundry
or our SUSE, perhaps, thank you. I mean, I'm not in contact because no one here is project
manager or team lead, let's say that, I would let another team member of us answer into that,
yes, of course, the RPM distributions are taken into account, and all the relatives
to Fedora, they're of course taken into account. The thing is, for now, let's say it's a quite
younger project, NFI, it's just two years since it has started the developing, and so
I would say that this is the reason why we're just talking about Fedora, Fedora, Fedora,
because this is our upstream where we do the testing, our CI runs on Fedora, and well,
I think that we definitely would be porting, or we would be very happy to see the NF5 land
in other RPM distributions. I think that's it.
Okay, thank you again. Thank you. Thank you, everyone.
Thank you.