Hello, folks. Welcome to my talk. I'm Akash Deep Dhar. Today I'm going to talk about Linux
distribution state of gaming. I'll talk a little bit about myself first. Basically, I'm
someone who has been contributing to Fedora project for around a couple of years before
they thought the folks who actually help the Fedora distribution as a corporate entity,
they thought that, well, I'm not going to leave anyway, so they might as well hire me.
The next thing that I find myself doing is actually working as a software engineer for
a team that manages infrastructure for Fedora as well as CentOS. It's called the community
platform engineering team. As well as, you know, just because Fedora is kind of close
to my heart, I mean, it's kind of CentOS at this point in time, but misappropriation.
I work for Fedora council as well as being the objective representative for the Fedora
website synapse team. Gaming has been a prime concern for me, especially having laptops
that don't quite run games. So the thing that I used to do is have distributions that can
actually have a greater headroom assigned to that game instead of running some fancy
stuff in the background. So that is what has been the entry point for Linux distributions
for me. So over the course of last five years, I have written and demonstrated multiple talks,
multiple articles around how to be able to run video games on GNLinux distributions, how
to be able to benchmark them, and while driver install is too while we're at it.
Right. So I watched this movie called Zootopia and there's this Fox character that I can't
remember the name of. So he tells that, you know, the best way of giving a talk is to
ask a question to themselves first and then answering that question. So I guess I'll do
that. So we can ask ourselves three questions about the state of gaming and Linux distributions.
The first being, is it popular? The second being, is it convenient to make happen? And
the third being, is it performant? Like why even consider gaming on Linux distributions
when there is some other consoles? There are other platforms which are actually willing
to do that. So it certainly is popular. I mean, we can totally thank our friends at
Valve for the Steam Deck and for other people who run a lot of games on their Android iPhones.
I mean, Android is Linux, all right. But then again, is it the way we kind of want it to
be popular? So there's this small asterisk over there. We have things for emulation.
We have things operating systems dedicated for running video games, like distributions
like Battlesale Linux, Lacca, which runs retro arch and nothing else on the bottom of it.
And there's this thing called Retropie, which runs emulation stations. So if you must have
gotten yourself a Raspberry Pi and looked for something in the Internet, some DIY tutorial,
it's probably one of the first five things you will end up seeing. And finally, consoles
that actually use Linux on the top of them. Speaking of convenience, it is convenient.
Is it convenient to run Linux distributions for gaming? And you most certainly will have
different opinions regarding the kind of configurations that you want to do. If you want to tailor
fit your stuff, get the frame rates that you want and the quality that you need, there
are more configurations to like bare bones wine, retro arch so that you can tailor fit
your stuff or something like Android phones or Steam Deck, which can do that for you.
And finally, we have performance. Now, I have seen this over the course of years running
video games on Linux, the things that are supposed to run on Windows, that if the games
run, well, if they do, they usually end up being 15 to 30% more performant. You can totally
find the references in the slide deck if the font's a bit too small, that, yeah, this
thing is actually the case. But what exactly is the sacrifice here? Also, I mean, I can
pass through a GPU. If I have this big GPU, I can pass it through virtual machines and
have near native performances instead of doing, say, on a hardware that is totally not okay
for a certain game to run. But, yeah, why exactly do I have those asterisks out there?
If it's performant, if it's convenient, if it's popular, then what's with the terms
and conditions, supply kind of thing that I have over there? And, well, there are things
that we're missing out. So one of the first things that we do is it is popular, people
are enthusiastic about it, but less people are enthusiastic about it. And it's usually
the people who would like to spend their hours configuring things, writing config files, hacking
stuff to be able to run some games on their desktop or their handheld devices that run
Linux distributions. And that's barely around 1.38%. And that's the service about where
I got that 1.38% from. It is something that has been going up since the last couple of
years. Here again, we have the friends at work to thank for for the Steam Deck that
we are getting increased usage. But a lot of these users are totally going unaccounted
for because telemetry is a big no-no for us. And we definitely advertise telemetry as
something that we should not do. And, well, when there are things like Lutris, things
like RetroPy, RetroArch, then PlayOnLinux, Wine, these tools are doing the best that
they can do. But guess what? We don't get to know how exactly are these being used.
And as a result, the publishers, they think that, well, Linux distributions, who uses
Linux distributions, why should we port our games in Linux distributions? We better not.
We might as well create them for other platforms. Well, I won't name any, but with comparatively
higher market share, right, of our consoles. Because guess what? Consoles are supposed
to be for gaming, not for writing code. And then, you know, third-party developers, they
don't bother. They don't really care. They are like, ah, fine. They'll use their stuff
to emulate our games on their platform. They call Wine an emulator. We know the difference.
They probably don't. So I go have my friends have a conversation
with my friends that, yeah, you play this game on Windows. Here's how it can run on
Linux. And they're like, oh, my God. That's too many configuration files. That's too many
hours of work. And all my friends are on Windows. So sorry about that, brother. But I'm going
to be at Windows as well. And the other person, they try installing games. But guess what?
It's a multiplayer game. So, and it's like, oh, no. We don't recognize this platform.
So you're cheating. That kind of stuff that totally puts people off. They don't want them
to be here even though they totally are not. Talking about convenience, it's, well, it's
convenient for some people. The some, you know, I kind of count myself in the minority
because I can totally go behind the screen, do hours of stuff. But for what about others?
You know, what about the folks who just want to spend some time playing games on a weekend?
You know, someone who have a busy life. So you don't expect them to actually sit behind
their computer screens for like five hours configuring stuff, right? You want them to
actually be able to play games on the get go. It does not quite happen that way for the
most parts. Few games work as it is. Some of them require minimal configuration, like
some slides here, some slides there, maybe some versions of DXVK. But others, they don't
work at all. And, you know, you don't get to know that they don't work unless you spend
hours of it banging your head on the wall, trying to make them work. And then you realize
that they really don't. So the convenience, like, they follow through steps. But just
because the Linux distributions are so fragmented, we have a certain version of package manager
in a certain distribution. There's a certain way, certain root FS are installed, stuff
like that. So you can't quite expect a certain steps to actually work on one distributions
and to be replicated on something else. There would be certain steps that would be required
in between and it only comes with experience. But can we expect experience? Of course not.
So people have difficulties with doing that. And then people don't really want to spend
time. And it's all valid because guess what? People are there to play games, not to become
contributors in an open source software, right? Finally about performance, right? Say, one
of the things that happens with performance is the fact that there are games that run
comfortably, right? All fine, good frame rates, good graphics whatsoever. At the very same
time, if you use that same distribution, you thought, oh, this runs Final Fantasy. I might
as well run Warframe with that. Then it won't happen. It won't even load up, let alone have
good frame rates in that. So there is some Taylor fitting required, but that Taylor fitting
is, you know, works for one thing, but it does not work for something else. So you don't
have this one size fits all kind of a solution for gaming, which is sad. But then again,
it is what it is right now. And well, there are some publishers who do not even support
these environments. They're like, nope, not this, not that, nothing at all. We won't let
Linux users play our games because that's not how we do things. And look, people are
able to get frame rates. I was able to get a lot of frame rates, good performance, but
there have been times when it has been all inconsistent since the such thing has happened
with my friends as well using a variety of Linux distributions. So it's definitely not
just for all Linux, but my friends who actually use Pop OS just because it allows for having
NVIDIA drivers installed from a get go. So you don't really have to pop open a terminal
and do some crazy voodoo according to my non-technical friends to be able to install drivers.
It just works from the get go. But guess what? Even they have some inconsistent performances.
And then there are ports that are for Linux, but just because they are not a lot of takers
here again, telemetry, just because people don't get to know that there are actually
people playing their games trying to work hard to actually make them compatible, people
pull them out even if there was a version at some point in time. Right, so if all I
have are complaints, is it all bad? Is it something that does not run at all? What is it like?
You know, it's quite the opposite. It's not bad. The community has been doing a great
job. If I were to look back 10 years ago, people had to use wine as it is. And it's
a tool that gets things done, but then again, if you want things to be done, things need
to be abstracted for you to be able to understand it. And if someone of a web developer is made
to understand the things that go behind the scene, oh my God, then it's totally not worth
of doing. So there are tools like Lutris, play on Linux that abstract the stuff that
wine do. So it's a lot better right now than it has ever been before. But then again, there
are things that we can totally do to make things a lot more better than they are right
now. So there's a silver lining. It's a small market share. People can be unsatisfied with
big config files and stuff like that. But here are six ways that I think it's all subjective.
There can be other things that people can think as well that I can add in my list and
make it 60 probably. But one of the things that people need to understand is if it were
really a technical challenge, right? So we have a lot of people working hard to make
these things work. Drivers, no matter how hard it can be for the proprietary drivers,
the proprietary blocks, the kernel modules to be loaded up, people are working hard.
But people are not understanding how exactly is it affecting or influencing the gamers,
the folks who actually use GNU Linux distributions to be able to play these games. So there should
be some way of open metrics, you know, some kind of telemetry that is not shady. It does
not look through your context and understand, oh, this person needs to have this at a certain
point in time. Not that kind of metrics, but rather what exactly is the tool, what exactly
are the workflows that are used in order to make these video games work. So these reliable
metrics should be implemented for the developers to understand that, yeah, their works are
indeed worth it. And for the publishers, because, oh, boy, they think that the market
share is small. So in order for the rise in market share, which has been, for the most
parts, the ones that we get to see from Steam, we should have more than that. So I don't know
if there are metrics in looters, bottles, or emulators. And I guess there is not, apart
from the ones that they themselves collect, because guess what? They really want to see
if their stuff works or not, and how exactly can they improve their own software. But does
it add up to the entire GNU Linux gaming metrics and make people understand that, yeah, folks
using looters, folks using bottles, folks using Steam Deck, folks using Android, they all
combine together as being a market share for this entire gaming. I don't think so at this
point in time, but this is something that we should definitely consider.
The next thing, of course, is to account for feedback and promote participation. So I have
seen in the course of the last many years that if you make people feel like they are
being heard, no matter what kind of project it is, if it's just creating some websites
or deploying things on the infrastructure, or be it about gaming. If people are heard,
if the features that they suggest, if the bugs that they tell is, you know, is bothering
them are implemented, chances are that they will tell their friends that this is something,
this is some kind of tool that they make use of and they should make use of as well. And
I like to think that reporting for bugs is also a very valuable contribution. So, you
know, being empathetic to the users, understanding, you know, by putting themselves on their
shoes, what kind of issues that they end up facing. And finally, understanding the tools
that people make use of. If there are a lot of dials, if there are a lot of drop-downs,
if there are a lot of things that people have to do before they are able to run their games,
it's probably not the most convenient way of doing so. So you can't quite expect a
person coming back home after a long day to be able to tweak those stuffs and make them
work. So the usability of them, how do we make it more convenient, should be something
that we should look into in these distributions, you know, kind of streamline the entire workflow
in order to make sure that people know where exactly they need to go to, to get a certain
function, to get a certain settings applied. And that's more about the convenience of,
you know, so that people can focus solely on the video games and not around the operating
system that's built for the sake of running games. Because trust me, if you have a PC,
operating video games are the one thing out of a thousand things that you will do. So
it just makes it a lot more easier to focus on what they want. For convenience, we totally
should be able to abstract complex things when we need to. So customization is fine.
It's one of the reasons why we are fragmented and I'm kind of thankful for it, so that I
have a choice that I can customize a distribution of my own kind to be able to make something,
to serve a certain purpose. But for the folks who don't need, it's going to be overwhelming.
They're going to be really scared of all those options put out there in front of them and
they'll be like, oh my God, no, definitely not. And they'll run back to the thing that
they were playing games on. So it's definitely not something that we would want to do. Being
able to provide a balance between the two of them and, you know, organically finding,
oh, fine, this person is scrolling down the menu. So probably it's looking for something
that's a lot more extensive than what we have provided for. Some kind of organic way to
find it and to be able to demonstrate how they can do it is a way that would strike
a good balance between the complicated looking stuff and the people who really want to get
their job done as quick as possible. Finally, for distributions that actually prioritize
these tools, these workflows, these applications, these should be available, like, natively
in their own repositories or there should be a way to be able to install them and not,
like, build from source or, like, dot-slashing them out of the blue because who runs shell
script files anyway, right? You should definitely read them. Drivers, codecs, kernel modules
and things like that, if you don't have a way to update them natively, trust me, it's
really a bad choice to be able to using that distributions. Say, people are here to play
games not to build software from source. Say, definitely we should consider having all of
these things packaged natively. And finally, to build standard workflows to be able to
test and quantify that, yeah, what is good performance, what is bad? Now, me, I can be
really biased towards good performance even if I see 60 frames per second on a 165-hertz
screen. I can tell that is good, but for someone else, it's like, oh, no, it's just like one
third of that frame rate. How do you call it a good performance? In that very case,
we need to understand and tell that, yeah, this is the criteria that was used to tell
that, yeah, this video game actually runs and this video game does not and could use
some more work before it's able to be, well, executing the way it should be. And when we
have all of these things in place, probably the publishers of AAA titles, popular ones
like that will be able to understand that, yeah, there is some kind of standards used
in this fragmented world of distributions to be able to understand that, yeah, if we follow
these rules to be able to create our games, it will have a compatibility with at least
85 percent, 75 percent, I'm saying this on the top of my head, but at least majority
of distributions will not have a problem and you won't be actually told to use a certain
distribution just because, well, your friend uses it.
So let's have a case study of Fedora Workstation in the end. So we have had distributions based
on the top of Fedora Linux distribution, Nobara Workstation, they have added meaningful
additions on the top, so to be able to make sure that people who really are willing to
focus on video gaming, they don't have to install much stuff on the top of it. And you
know, it's heavily popular with the folks who develop bottles and looters because they
get the latest and greatest stuff in the official repository, so they don't really have to go
out of their way to do so. And then the required tooling to be able to run these games, drivers,
and the ability to install them from RPM Fusion just in case their proprietary in nature is
totally possible. And the fact that the GNOME desktop, well, what can I say, it's just one
of the great ones. I'm a bit biased. Say, you know, it totally keeps the workflows aligned
and well, unintuitive. And finally, talking about the consistent performance, well, let's
just say that the configurations should be done in a modular manner so as to make sure
that if I do certain thing, I can copy that stuff and give it to my friend. Here's, you
know, you don't have to spend many hours like I did, paste that stuff and this should
be running. Or something a bit more polished than that, but basically, no more repeating
of efforts. And, you know, customizable enough to be actually minimize the footprint of the
operating system, the distribution itself, to be able to dedicate more of that performance
over to the actual video games. And that's pretty much about it. I'm totally open to
your questions.
Thank you for your talk. I got the impression that you're pushing for telemetry to be used
more. Would that be right?
Well, let's just say I'm pushing for an open telemetry. So you get to see what kind of information
is being shared with the folks and what folks are you sharing that with. So you don't think
that, oh, it's the shady number of information and with the shady number of folks that it
is shared with, right? So telemetry is important. There are software that have telemetry like
pre-built and they have it natively done, but then again, it's just a limited set of telemetry
people. Once we unify this and have a place where we can say that, yeah, it's coming from
them, so there's something that we can improve upon in the distributions level so that we
can understand that, yeah, a certain application or an emulator is acting up and there's something
that we can act on. Any more questions?
Hey, thank you very much. I think on the telemetry side, there is a fundamental metric that the
developers look at which is sales. So I think the main thing is like there is a sort of
1-2% audience on Linux that will buy games. I think that's pretty clear. I think there
are other advantages for developers having Linux users in early. We tend to report bugs
and if we do that in a helpful and non-annoying way, then we can be an asset particularly
to the trend of people doing early access releases and wanting engaged users. So I think
that's the thing that you can think about supporting early access games, supporting
stuff on edge I think is helpful. The other side is like if you just want to play games,
by far the easiest thing to do is ignore your distribution, install Steam, Proton handles
the config wrapping around wine really conveniently and the best game of the last five years was
released natively on Linux anyway, so play Slay the Spire. Thank you.
Thank you so much. One of the things that you mentioned that probably we could have
some kind of telemetry done in a central basis and the fact that early access can be something
that we can provide to people using Linux. It's one of the things that we can totally
use to actually increase our market share and make people feel like it's worth it if
you give it a try and people might end up actually buying it. When it comes to Proton,
I mean, jeez, they have done a marvelous job by abstracting what's not important or what's
totally really, really scary. Might scare people away out of the room, leave their Steam
decks that they have purchased with their hard earned money and to be able to play games
while they're on the go. So it's some kind of abstraction that keeps things convenient
that we are all looking for and there should be a balance so people should go and be like,
jeez, it's so abstracted that I can't do anything anymore, right? So that should definitely
not happen. All right, folks, I'm going to give way to the next talk. Please find me
over here if you have more questions. Thank you so much again.