I'm here thanks yes hello good morning and nice day for foster them hope you
had a nice evening yes let's start with the torque matrix RTC matrix beyond
instant messaging let's get that so first of all what is matrix maybe we
have some redundancy a little bit here but for the sake of the recording and
I'll repeat some of what Matthew already showed us so basically the idea is an
open and federated secure and decentralized real-time communication
network and the use cases are many for it so the obvious one is of course the
interoperable chat but we are also aiming for voice of IP applications or
even VR applications but you can also think of something like IOT data and
this is so most of those use cases you're quite familiar with and what's
the well-known event layer so for a chat for instance you have a store and
forward semantics however the cool thing about matrix is that it is yeah
constructed such a way that it is de-central it is federated and what's
for me pretty cool and important is this replicated and end-to-end encrypted so
for instance if you're a client on one of those hosts here and you're attaching
to one home server and you're joining a room from another home server at that
moment the rooms replicated and everything is end-to-end encrypted it
is pretty cool it's like like a git git clone something like that similar with
an automatically your synchronization mechanism on top of it I'm quite sure
that you're very familiar with it you could also summarize it matrix is a
de-distributed real-time database and I can recommend this talk here from my
colleague Andy it's a very nice overview of what the specifics here on the
other side this talk today is about matrix RTC and now what is the
definition of matrix RTC what it was it so there's basically it's the world
first de-central federated real-time channel or communication platform and
it's packed an msc341 and msc3898 and it's depicted here what basically the
idea is from a client perspective you have a peer-to-peer semantics and we
don't have a storage or persistency in it but you can exchange data with a low
latency and a low jitter from one client to the other and another interesting
thing here is that the business logic is owned by the clients though in most
recent RTC platforms or video conferencing platforms you have in
something like an SFU and an application server and here the idea really is the
business logic is in the clients let's have a look at some use cases so the
most obvious of course is video conferencing right that this is what
everybody would you know assume when you talk about RTC but we can also have
the embedded version here so let's just take a normal matrix client and put a
widget into it and then have all your video conferencing or go to the VR world
or the the the matrix interpretation of the meta-words which is called third
room everything can be realized using matrix RTC and the cool thing here is
that you can also think about a hybrid use case so for instance imagine we
have a whiteboard like we have this here so we can use for fast UX the matrix
RTC layer such when I make a stroke now that it's more or less immediately at the
other whiteboards but for persistency we can just use the room the distributed
database so what are the base building blocks which we use to create matrix
RTC so first of all of course we need something like a real-time communication
framework and the obvious choice at the current point in time is web RTC because
it has a quite good adoption it's in all the web browsers and there are a lot of
a lot of SDKs around we can use but going forward maybe you can also sing
something like web transport or web codex to to replace it so we are not
mandating web RTC but for the time being that is of course the framework to use
then for the signaling that's quite obvious that we use matrix for it rates
and then to make it scale you might optionally also want to use a back end
component a focus this could either be an MCU or an SFU
so now as I stated the back end component is optional let's have a look
on start matrix RTC without and back end component so having a look at the
connection models though the obvious and the simplest one to start with is peer
to peer right that's just easier create a peer connection and then you have a
they have a data layer and then you can play around with matrix RTC it's getting
a little bit more complicated if you want to to have an RTC session with
more than two people so then we spin up a full mesh and then it really depends on
the use case how many people can join if you have a look maybe at the the use case
of a video conference then you would need to distribute and minus one media
up links and down links which is then limited by your internet connection and
if you haven't had least in Germany in average DSL connection it would scale to
up to five to eight participants and this is something we're currently using in
an element call to element call at the current point in time is based on this
full mesh setup or was we have some news today the the vision which also really
scales and would allow a large scale RTC sessions is what we call cascaded
selective forwarding units and it's depicted here so what you would have
you would have an selective forwarding unit as long side with your home server
it's optional but you can have it and by this we then would allow a further
scaling and can really yeah using the cascading concept to dynamically crawl
to any size we have to test it but that's the theory so far the signaling
here of course is also carried out over matrix and for the for the specifics for
the SFU we have this MSE 3898 which handles then all the the magic of the
cascading and so on and so forth from a setup perspective if you want to scale
large network and large RTC network the idea is that you place the SFU's as
close as you can to your customers or to your clients and to ensure a proper
internet so this ensures a proper internet connection with low jitter low
packet loss and then you have the SFU's placed in a strong network center and
have a good interconnection and by this setup you have yeah that's that's that's
the best you can do in terms of media quality
so what we did we started with an SFU which is capable to speak the matrix
flavor of of RTC it's a prototype which was handed over from Sean from the
inventor of the pine stack and it's a Golang based web RTC implementation we
added the matrix bits to it we wrote a lot of it it's early stage but we have
support for audio channels we have support for video channels and screen
sharing and on top of that recently we also added so-called similar cast
support similar cast is you can imagine that maybe have to go step back so in
the full mesh mode you have a literally a peer-to-peer connection to each of
those clients and by adding some signaling you can the receiver can tell
the sender oh I'm struggling with a network connection can you please adapt
your your network bandwidth from from the encoding site and this is a little
bit harder if you're having a central point the SFU so here the trick is
that the sender will provide several or media quality levels and then on the
SFU the client can decide which one to choose low quality mid quality and high
quality and this is called similar cast and we all already have basic support
for similar cost in our selective forwarding unit matrix is known for
privacy and end-to-end encryption and in the full mesh set up of matrix RTC
that's quite easy because you have the transport layer which ensures end-to-end
encryption but if you terminate a peer connection on an SFU the transport
layer is of course terminated and hence we need media encryption and this is the
missing part here so using insertable streams you need going forward to
implement end-to-end encryption on the client side that such that the media is
encrypted on the client send over and then it's not an issue on the SFU for
this specific topic matrix RTC and cascaded foci or a selective forwarding
units we have later a dedicated talk for my colleague Shimon it's the in-depth
talk cascaded foci it will be in this no not in this room it will be online at 2
p.m. this day
so now we have an idea what the vision of matrix RTC is and what we can do with
it we have seen so far the use cases let's come back to element call I think
we demonstrated it last year right yes very early very early and after one year
you could imagine something happened so first recap what's element call it so
initially it was developed on the green field as a single page application in
the cool story here it's just a matrix client right it's not for chat it's a
matrix client and the implementation was using the full mesh so without a
backend component what's new so after this year first of all in our site or not
site project our partner project hydrogen we also have call support right
now and it's also working interoperably so you can start with hydrogen the call
and join with element call and the other way around we added the SFU bits to
element call and we integrated it into element web so in element app we now
have two flavors of element call we have a crew call experience we just press
the crew call button and we have a dedicated video rooms which is pretty
cool so the semantic of this room is that when you press or click on this
room you're asked to join the conference immediately
the question is how to embed element call into a matrix client in general so in
theory you could just implement the msc's but that would be very expensive
because then you need to implement in each platform expensive in terms of
engineering bandwidth so all requirements are one implementation which fits
all and the idea is yeah that we embedded element call or the embedded
element call needs to share the same underlying matrix client and room in
order to not waste resources or to have device proliferation so the idea is
quite obvious let's use a widget for it also short recap on widgets what is a
widget a widget is basically an application living in a matrix room
it's simply an embedded iframe and it's yeah a small form factor web
application html JavaScript the widget is embedded within a room and can
communicate with matrix clients and therefore from the matrix client through
the widget API and this widget API is a defined post message API basically a
widget is able to request permissions and to perform on actions on the user's
behalf something like posting into a room receiving specific event types and so
on and so forth to have a more easy a way of approaching widgets we have also
have a widget SDK which is written in JavaScript and TypeScript it's basically a
web app and now here we have an overview a few about element call in the
various flavors so in the single page application the mode it's just the
matrix client using the client server API and in the widget mode here we are
going through the widget API over the underlying matrix client and then to the
home server the abstraction layer client server API versus widget is a really
thin so from a development perspective that was really easy to implement yeah
so the solution is it's just a widget it's web RTC in a web view and this is
the nice thing so the the whole web RTC stack to implement on various
platforms is quite painful but if you can just a web view where this is
included for free that's that's a thing we needed to extend the widget API to
add some missing bits specifically it where the 2d-wise messages and to
access the turn server also spec in the msc's and this this whole concept we
call matroshka embedding where we have a web view hosting widgets in the
various clients and that could be a web client but it could also be the native
clients like the IOS and the intro lines and hence we have the solution one
implementation that fits all
let's have a demo right
so what you see here basically is just the desktop application of element
element nightly on the left hand side you can see the various rooms with
various flavors so here this is a general room and he has already a
conference started so if you press it you will join it and at the top here we
have a so-called video room and you know if you join it directly prompted to to
join a conference and what you can also see here is a chat so let's join it hello
I raised the volume here so hi Enrico hi Simon yeah welcome to foster them what
we can do here right now is that we have various flavors so we have a new
layout here which we call large crits design and you can yeah change the tile
sizes and I also added here some debug information and you can see that the
small video on the top left receives the low quality stream whereas the large
screen or a large tile on the bottom receives the mid-quality stream hey Dave
hello so ah and hi yeah so and now we want to carry out an experiment I have a
QR code here hopefully I find it yeah and I encourage everybody to join the call
and to crash our SFU let's low test it sorry it's chrome
yeah yeah I will do a pet what is the resolution the projects are good enough
so let's see so of course if it's not working then we can blame the wife I
hear right
four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven streams working for me at the moment.
Uh-huh.
Better than you.
Ah, no, no, no, it's recovering, it's recovering.
So we plan a second demo later the day with the talk from Simon.
So, yeah, but so how many do we have?
Is that as good?
You've got aspergerosia, bugs all over the place.
It depends.
Yes.
Okay, let's say I leave it in the background, play around with it,
and we go back to the talk.
Okay.
So, what's next in the matrix RTC ecosystem?
Of course, we want to implement the whiteboard, at least the hybrid version of the whiteboard.
Then the very important thing really is to start with the insertable streams to also have the entrant encryption in case of using the SFU.
With respect to the selective forwarding units, we need to implement the focus selection logic.
So if you remember the graph where we had the, or the picture where we had the home servers alongside the SFUs alongside with the home servers,
we sketched out a nice algorithm where you can automatically choose the right one.
And this is something we need to implement right now.
Yeah, and then obviously the cascading.
This has not started the implementation, but yeah, we need to carry out.
On the similar cost layer, we also have some optimizations in mind.
For instance, I think it's only a good idea to upload your video to the SFU if on the other side someone consumes this video stream.
So this is an optimization we can add.
And I think also the switching point where when you change the layer from high quality to low quality, there's also some room for improvement.
On top of that, we need to care a little bit more about network bandwidth rate control.
This is an important thing we need here, such that the SFU also feeds back information back to the client,
such that the client is then in a good position to adapt the local video or audio encoders.
And finally, we want to extend the call support in Hydrogen and add the SFU bits to it.
And now maybe some of you are wondering a little bit why Matthew is sitting here with his classes.
Yeah, and now let's head over.
I have some questions.
So what we have so far seen was the obvious use case for MatrixRTC, which is a video conferencing solution.
But I told you earlier that we also have something like the Metaverse interpretation of Matrix.
We call it third room.
Yeah, and in a half minute.
Any questions, though, on Florian?
Yeah, it's a hard Q&A part.
Hopefully this thing is going to work.
Apologies for being the idiot with a VR headset on.
Hopefully this thing is going to start streaming in a second.
So I wanted to talk about third room, which is the spatial collaboration platform that we have built on top of Matrix.
And I'm going to slightly mess around with trying to get this to work at the right resolution,
because it's going to look crap if it's not at the right res.
How do we change the resolution these days in MacOS?
Anybody know how to actually change as refresh rate advanced?
That's not helpful.
You can talk.
Oh, really?
Let me just check the stream itself, because if it's working alright, then we're all good.
That's not me.
Jan, is that your fault that it's live streaming here?
Oh, it's the wrong one. Thank you.
Too many dev rooms. You should probably be using the same one.
Ah, 2001 online dev room.
No, it's not the online dev room. The normal dev room.
What is it?
Matrix under real time.
I can't spell Matrix. This is going well.
That one. Right. Thank you.
Are we sure? That looks totally squashed. That's literally what I'm trying to fix right now.
How can it be to actually set a resolution on this thing these days?
How about I press that button, where we're going to go to...
Yeah, so it's gone to four by three, but it wants to do four by three everywhere,
so it's not four by three, it's 16 by nine.
Let's go to that. Will that work?
Is that coming in on the stream already? Just check this.
It'll be worth it, don't worry.
On the plus side, the Oculus thing is on KXN, which is good.
Right, yeah, this is looking good.
So, let me actually bring up third room.
So, the point of third room is that it's a tiny team.
Sorry.
Hi, everybody. Welcome to my talk on third room,
which is a project, a tiny project done by three people,
Robert and AJ, AJ also famous for doing Sydney as a Matrix client,
which is trying to show people that Matrix is way more than chat and VoIP.
I know that it's cool to look at 3D stuff these days and go,
I don't like 3D, but honestly, I think this is incredibly interesting
in showing the potential of what we have to build on top of Matrix today.
Now, the way it works is that you've got Hydrogen SDK going
and basically providing a plain old Matrix client.
And if I jump into this room here, which is hash presentation
on thirdroom.io, if people want to play along at home,
feel free to come and jump in and heckle my presentation.
And you can see that this is a virtual world going and sitting in browser.
If I pull up the frame rate, which is obviously control shift S,
you can see it's actually going at 60 frames a second, Amandino's stuck in the floor.
It's running at 60 frames a second in browser at, well, 1080p, as we all just saw,
which is pretty impressive for a fairly complicated scene that we have going on here.
And the way that thirdroom works is quite unusual.
And it's properly multi-freaded in browser.
It's using an entirely new game engine that the team basically put together.
And I should hasten to add, I've basically been encouraging people
rather than actually working on this, but Robert's in San Fran.
And so it'll be cruel and unusual to get him to do this and talk.
And I've even got some slides here.
And it's showing the scripting that is built in that I'll talk about in a minute.
Now, the interesting thing is that we're using shared arrayed buffers to go
and share data between the main thread and a bunch of worker threads
using post-message between these and then the Atomics APIs in the browser
so that you can actually have proper multiple threads in order to have the rendering thread
running completely independently from the gaming thread that does physics
and the main thread that does React and does Hydrogen
because we've embedded Hydrogen in the React app here as well as Matrix.
So, I'm going to go to the next slide.
Here are some of the main threads.
We've got React, Matrix and WebRTC happening.
And we have spatial audio in here.
So if I actually unmute myself.
Ooh, I've got first for myself on my own talk.
That's annoying. Let me pause that.
Amandine, are you still out there somewhere?
You want to come over and say something to me?
Is anybody else?
I'll go over to you, say something.
Can you hear me? Yeah, I can.
So if we had headphones on at this point and I turn this way and you say something.
Hello.
It's coming out the left speaker and you have to believe me.
And look the other way and it's coming out.
Honestly, it helps the immersive experience massively that we're going using spatial audio
to go and position where things are here.
Whilst we're wandering around here,
you can see that we've got, at the moment, generic avatars.
But if you walk around a bit,
you can see her moon walking backwards for whatever reason.
I'm sure you can also go forwards.
There we go.
And fly for that matter.
And so the B button lets you fly in this so you can go and jump around like so.
And so, ooh, you're spoiling my talk.
So if we go down here, then on the game thread, we've got a bunch of rust.
We have the ability to run arbitrary WebAssembly scripts,
which is sitting in a sandbox,
which allows you to basically add any arbitrary functionality into the world.
From a pure matrix perspective, this is probably the most exciting thing here.
Now, if you remember IRC and Merck scripting,
the ability to run arbitrary scripts on your IRC client,
this is effectively allowing you to define bots and arbitrary functionality in matrix,
which run inside your client, inside the sandbox,
and the actual data is stored in your room.
Now, this whole thing is a matrix room.
If I go and hit Enter, then you can see a bunch of users there.
And I can say, hello, world.
And if I go back to my element client,
and if I literally join presentation on thirdroom.io for a matrix.org,
then you can see I'm being saying, yeah.
And I can say, yeah, to you too.
And hopefully, hang on.
Well, I've got traffic running one way.
Interesting.
Well, we should be seeing messages coming into the room as well,
because it is, oh, there we go.
It's just a plain old hydrogen overlay
that is being rented in React for the contents of the room.
Now, the actual geometry of the room,
if we start flying around some more,
looks like this is actually a big GLTF or a single GLTF asset.
This thing is just sitting in the media repository in the room.
It's just a file that is GLTF, the transfer format for OpenGL,
that has been uploaded there, and also any scripts in the room,
like the one which is executing the,
letting me press on the buttons here.
Again, there's a bit of, I think, JavaScript using the QuickJS engine
that has gone and compiled down the JavaScript to WebAssembly in real time.
It's pretty cool that you literally write it in JavaScript,
and then the engine sucks it up, turns it into Wasm,
and runs it within that sandbox.
So you could argue it's a little bit perverse
to be taking JavaScript, compiling it to WebAssembly,
and then running it from within a JavaScript environment,
but it gives you a hell of a lot more safety
than you would if we were just, I know,
having random blobs of JavaScript running here.
On the render thread, we are using WebGL2,
and we're using FreeJS to manage the actual driving of WebGL.
But the scene itself is, the scene itself is
managed using a really cool technology called BitECS,
that was actually created by Nate,
one of the developers before he started working on,
before they started working on third room.
And BitECS is an entity component system
where you basically track the state of the world,
the objects that exist within it, their transformations,
and it's done with arrays in JavaScript,
and it turns out that if you structure your arrays
intelligently enough in JavaScript,
you can get as good as WebAssembly performance,
and it's one of the other secrets
to the crazy performance that we have here.
So this isn't a scene graph API under the hood,
like A-frame, if anybody ever played with A-frame,
instead it's using the BitECS.
Then another thing which is interesting here
is that everything is triple buffered.
So in a kind of traditional game engine,
you just have one sort of buffer that you write data into
and the renderer reads it out,
and you have some kind of locking system
to make sure that it doesn't collide.
Whereas here, we have lot free data structures,
letting things go as rapidly as possible
with the various different bits of the engine
writing into this shared triple buffer,
as is shared array buffer, which is then juggled
effectively between the various different threads,
and it means that the render thread can run at the native speed
of whatever device, which is particularly useful
if it's a less powered device than my MacBook Pro here,
and then the game engine that is actually rendering
what's going on can go at its own speed,
so you totally decouple the two
and you get as high a frame rate as you can.
And I think that, oh yeah, and finally,
lots of fun stuff going on with asset optimization pipeline.
Particularly the textures have been highly compressed
using these fun codecs.
I think it's called universal basis format from binomial and KTX,
and one of the things we've done to cheat to bootstrap
third room is to build a pipeline from Unity
where you can take existing Unity assets,
like this scene here is one that we bought off a Unity asset store,
and then export it as proper open standardized JLTF,
somewhat liberating the contents
from the slightly proprietary world of Unity
in order to get content in more rapidly,
and then compress it down,
and there are lots of fun things,
like it has instancing support built in,
so if you start generating lots of objects,
like the physics engine here,
I know, go and create a whole bunch of objects
and attack the various people who are wandering around in here,
or they love me for it,
then this is basically just the same JLTF asset.
What are you doing?
Going and being created multiple times.
All the textures are sprighted,
so there's just one great big thing.
There's also some really interesting extensions to JL
that we've contributed by the Kronos group,
particularly if you look at,
if we grab one of these Mirables,
which are mainly used for debugging purposes,
let's grab that one,
and if I run around with it, or I fly around with it,
you should see that the reflection changes,
and there we go, like if I go between zones there,
it needs to be tuned a bit,
but basically rather than ray tracing,
which would be incredibly time consuming,
instead we have lots of different probes
hanging around the scene that allow you to,
so I'm hitting myself in the face with the ball,
a common problem,
that as you run around,
you can see the reflection changes.
It's pretty nasty if you do it rapidly,
but if you're doing it more slowly like this,
then it's quite a subtle but nice effect,
and it's even better when it's on not perfect Mirables,
if you look at, say, Dave,
if you walk backwards, if you can hear me,
or go into the light or out of the light,
then you'll actually see a fairly subtle shadowing effect,
as it's gone and figured out where the shadows are there.
Right, God, it's cool to see all the people running around in here.
So, what else can I show you?
So we're going to launch TEP Preview 2 this next week,
and this is the first time anybody has seen TEP Preview 2,
and I have 10 minutes here, left hand,
and TEP Preview 1 is sort of what we've been looking at here,
except it didn't have scripting.
We've already shown some of the scripting here,
but one of the big things that have been added,
and let's pray that this thing works,
is WebVR.
So, hopefully, if I go to the Oculus streaming thing,
which I had a second ago,
I should have possibly cleaned this up first.
Of course, it stopped working.
Whilst I get this thing back in again,
and everything is going wrong,
apparently I've got to recalibrate the entire thing.
So I apologize for using proprietary technology,
but unfortunately there aren't any open source headsets
which do the trick yet.
Let me go, and let me try to cast this up,
and unfortunately it takes ages for the screen casting
to kick in for some reason,
but I'll go as quick as I can, bump,
and cast, and computer go.
WebXR is a really cool technology.
It's been there for ages now, since about 2017,
built into browsers like Firefox and Chrome, obviously,
and also, interestingly, the browser that your Oculus Quest
like this, or Quest Pro, has built into it,
which is based on Chromium.
It has awful screen casting support, as you can see,
and I started at screen casting,
and something is happening in the depths of Facebook,
trying to figure out how to actually get this
onto the screen here, but hopefully it will come through,
assuming I've got internet connectivity.
Here it is, thank God, and I can start talking,
and I apologize for...
I'm going to focus on...
Oh, interesting.
I'm going to focus on Florent rather than embarrassing everybody else,
but let's just use a stationary boundary, confirm.
Right, so the browser here sits there.
I'm not going to update this right now,
but here is some third room,
and if I continue into third room as guest,
you can see this is just a static,
boring old web browser just sitting here.
Worth noting that third room uses OIDC entirely,
so this thing here is actually a skinned key cloak.
I'm going to say I'm not a bot,
I'm not going to bother giving myself a name,
and then Captcha failed.
Brilliant, thanks, Google.
I'm going to have to type in third room,
except caffeine and stress
means my ability to use a stupid keyboard like this
is going to be fun.
Okay, back to third room here.
There's a streaming, okay?
Okay, brilliant.
Let's go to login, go back to third room,
continue as guest.
This time, hope that it's not going to make me pick
stupid things, right?
Good, continue.
Accept the T's and C's.
Honestly, the using a key cloak for this
is really, really fun.
And very anticlimatically,
we end up with eventually,
once you load connectivity,
a 2D version of third room
just sitting right here.
So isn't it amazing?
By the way, that just loaded from
indexedDB local storage.
But the fun thing is hopefully,
come on, you can do it.
You can see it's actually struggling quite a lot
in this, but if I press the old X button,
there, that's why I have to close the
welcome to third room dialogue, here it is.
Come on.
Enter XR, thank God for that.
Then I can see Florian, hello Florian.
But more excitingly, hopefully,
if I stay in the right place,
there we go, you can see that I'm actually
in the third room environment right now.
And this is genuinely cool.
This is running at 90 frames a second for me,
right now.
And if I go and press some buttons to crates,
and oh God, ow!
Some crates, like that massive crate,
let me get rid of that.
You can see it's actually hooked up
to the normal physics engine,
so I can go and pull that,
and throw it into the audience,
which is no way surreal to be going
and flipping back and forth.
And then back in the normal world again.
At the moment, we've just got basic things
like the joystick and hung up,
hooked up to it.
It's got a kinematic controller,
and am I running out of, oh no,
thank you Florian.
What else can I show you?
We can jump, we can spawn more objects.
I can go up to that glitter globe,
and oh, sorry, mirrored ball.
It's running faster than I can run after it.
That's awkward.
And theoretically, if I was a little bit close
to the bloody thing, I'd be able to grab it
and pick it up, et cetera.
So this is pretty cool honestly.
It's as good as the native non-WebVR
closed stuff that Facebook,
or MetaHorizons does.
And the entire thing is open.
And they built on the surgery engine.
How am I doing for time? Three minutes.
In which case, I'll very quickly go,
and sorry, thanks for that.
I will start looking at random emissaries,
go back into this,
and just look at some other things we've done.
In fact, this one is really cool.
Let's just flip into this one,
because this is a really complicated bit of WASM.
It's actually an audio-reactive widget,
which is sitting here.
As you can see, as I yell at it,
it goes and changes size.
There's a whole bunch of C code
that has been compiled down to WASM
to show how you can have interactive things
sitting inside the scene.
Another example is slightly less excitingly.
A chatbot echo service.
So if I go into here and say hello,
and then do echo hello with a slash command,
it says hello back to me.
Now, the echo that's happening down there
is actually being done from the widget API of Matrix,
going into WebAssembly, talking to, I think,
a JavaScript service, and then echoes back.
You can see we have a slight bug sometimes
with scripting where it loads two worlds at the same time,
and that's pretty surreal.
That's what happens if London got combined with Mars.
Final thing here...
What was I going to show you?
Oh, yeah, is this guy,
which is a bit silly, but fun anyway.
This time I'll remember to refresh
as fun as it is to have the scenes combined,
so you might recognize this from a certain film.
And if we actually look at the script
for this particular room,
if I can figure out how to get out of full screen mode,
the script here is, again,
just sitting in the media repository.
It's a little bit of JavaScript
to use the WebSceneGraph API,
which is a new API that we've created.
We hope it will become a W3 standard
for manipulating scene graphs.
If you click on the TV,
you basically get a node by name to TV,
and then every frame you'd see
if the TV is being pressed,
and if it is, then you enable the matrix material.
And the end result is if I go here,
and I click on the TV,
then, predictably enough, you end up in a matrix-style world,
and I've got it in third-person view,
which is also new with Tet Preview 2
and Clipback and forth.
This is super early, but you can imagine
this is basically a platform for doing
any kind of real-time collaborative app.
It could be digital twins,
it could be smart cities,
GIS applications.
It's as powerful and as flexible as the Web,
but for real-time.
Thank you very much.
APPLAUSE
And we have no time for questions.
Time for one question.
Is there one question?
Oh.
I wanted to ask, where can we be
in custom avatars support?
It will be coming in the next release,
after Tet Preview 2.
I mean, the hard bit of actually rigging up the engine
and doing all the inverse kinematics,
and if you run around with the current avatars,
you can now trip over things, which is very important.
But suffice it to say,
we're focusing on the engine rather than the assets.
And also, this is at a point
where people can start contributing things.
So if you've got amazing assets,
and you've caught the maximum rig,
then they should just drop straight in.
All right.
Cool.
APPLAUSE