All right. Well, hello everyone. You'll notice I'm not Ben. This is Ben. There's three of
us here to talk to you about different things, all about improving clients and making them
as fast as you would normally expect them to be. So, first of all, my name is Keegan.
I'm going to be talking about sign and sync. And then you've got Ben, going to talk about
Russ Eskay, and Mara about Element X. So, first of all, sign and sync, and a bit about myself.
I'm a staff software engineer at Element, and I've worked on many different projects over
the years, and more recently working on things like Dendrite and Peer to Peer, and sign and sync.
But first of all, what even is sign and sync? So, for context, sign and sync,
the current sync mechanism in Matrix is really, really slow. So, if you have, you know,
you go and open up your mobile app after a weekend away or something like that,
it takes a little while to sync. It could take 30 seconds or a minute,
depending on how many rooms are on your account. And this is kind of bad, right?
We'd like it to sync instantly. And the whole point of sign and sync is trying to make that happen,
trying to make it sync instantly, or virtually instantly. There was a talk last year on the
online POSDEM. If you want to know more information about the deep dive of how sign and sync works,
and there's a QR code there, but I'm not going to be covering too much detail about how sign and
sync works, other than enough to kind of fill in the gaps if you have no idea what this is.
So, at a high level, sign and sync works by sorting and filtering. So, you can see here,
you've got all the rooms on the user's account, and then you can filter that set of rooms down
in some way. So, for example, you could filter it based on, like, I want encrypted rooms,
or I want DM rooms, things like that. And then you can apply some sort of sorting operation to
them. So, you might say, sort them by the room name, or you could say, sort by recency. So,
like, the last timestamp in the room, or by the number of notification counts, number of unread
messages and stuff that mention your name, and that sort of thing. And then you can request the
first five rooms, 10 rooms, 20 rooms, and things like that. Also, the rooms themselves, you can
filter the room state using sign and sync. So, in normal sync, you will go and get all of the
room state. And if there's a lot of room state, that's not great. So, in sign and sync, you can
specify, I'm only interested in, like, the topic of the room, and whether it's encrypted or not,
and that's it. This is a pretty big change to how matrix works today. So, how is this actually
going to, like, how are we actually going to do this in practice? So, in practice, there is a go
process, which is the sign and sync proxy, which I've been working on for over a year now, which
has a Postgres database attached, and it will go and do sync v2 requests on your behalf to an
upstream server. It could be synapse, it could be dendrite, whatever, it doesn't really matter,
it could be conduit. And the important thing here is that this proxy exposes a sign and sync API.
So, it exposes a new endpoint for a new sync endpoint, and then a client can go and try the
sign and sync API and see how it feels for them. So, they don't need to have a particular
implementation on synapse, they'll wait for these implementations to land. You can try it on your
own server if you run a proxy. In terms of a protocol level, what this looks like is you can
see here you've got some lists, it's a list object, and then you can specify things like things we
talked about before. So, you can say you've got the ranges there, you've got, so that's how many,
like, the top-end rims that you want, the sort ordering that you want, as well as any filters
you apply here. And here you can see we're filtering by isDMTrue, and that's going to be used to
populate the people tab, say, on Element Web. You also have these things called rim subscriptions.
They are kind of like the rim lists, but this is when you know the specific rim ID. So, if you
follow a permalink, which may include the rim ID, or if you, you know, if you refresh the page and
you know that, you know, this person was currently viewing this rim, that room may not be in this
list, right? So, you would need to subscribe to that room directly because you know the rim ID.
And typically, as well, the kinds of information you want here is different. So, in here, we are
requesting all the state in the rim and a much higher timeline element because this is being
used to populate the actual full room view. The response is very similar, as well. So,
you have a list object here, and then you get a list of rim IDs that are used to populate
the correct ordering here. And then you also have a top-level rims array, a rims object,
and then that's just a key value map where the keys are the rim IDs, and then the values are
all the data that you requested. So, these all get aggregated together, which I will speak about
a bit later. In terms of what's new, so if you followed Siding Sync, then you might be like,
okay, I know all this, but well, what's actually happened over the past year? We have clients
now that run Siding Sync. So, this is from Element Web. It's got a nice scary warning there. So,
you know, it's great. It all works on web, but also it actually works on mobile devices as well,
thanks to the Rust SDK, which I'll leave for Ben to talk about. So, there's also a whole bunch
of new extension MSCs. So, extension MSCs are an idea of trying to break up the complexity
of Siding Sync, because the Sync API is by far one of the most or not the most complicated part
of the client server API, and trying to put everything into one MSC is going to be doomed
to failure. So, we're trying to specify a core part of the MSC, a core part of what is syncing,
which is the syncing rooms, and working out the sorts and the filter arguments. And then,
we're leaving two extensions, all the extra stuff on top. And the idea is that you can opt in to
any of these things. So, if your client doesn't do receipts, then great, don't subscribe to receipts,
don't even enable this extension. Briefly, how these extensions work. So, these two extensions
go together because they're ultimately used to make encryption work in encrypted rooms. So,
you can see, or actually, you can't see it all. Here is an encrypted event. So, there's basically,
you have to trust me, there's a ciphertext here with lots of gibberish effectively. And then,
you need a room key to go decrypted into your normal text. The way that works is that you need to
get keys via your two device messages. That's why they go together. The other thing here is that
it implements another MSC called Dropping Sales Center Device Messages. You can barely see it
on here, but this is an output from Postgres, which is trying to work out how many unreads
or unacknowledged two device events are there for a given user device. And you might think that
might be, say, a hundred, maybe a thousand tops. It turns out this can be a lot. This is several
hundred thousand unread or unacknowledged two device events. And it turns out when I analyzed
a lot of this, this was almost entirely down to room keys being requested and then either
canceled or successfully sent. So, this MSC 3944 basically says, hey, if you request a room key
and then you subsequently cancel that request, you're going to go and delete those two device
messages. So, they don't just keep stacking up in this way. And that obviously really helps reduce
the amount of bandwidth for sign sync as well. The other thing we've got is account data. So,
if you wonder what account data does, if you've ever used the breadcrumbs thing at the top here
on Element Web, that's synchronized using account data. Also, account data is really,
really useful for working out accurate notification counts. So, at the bottom here, you can just
about see that you've got some messages here. You've got a message in a timeline. This is encrypted.
And it says here, notification count one. Notification counts are the gray numbers.
And you've got a highlight count of zero, which is the red number. And yet on the UI,
you can see that it's a red number and it's gone to one. So, some things happened here where the
client has worked out that, oh, I should use this as a highlight count, not a notification count.
It's overwritten what the service told it. And what's happened here is that the client has
decrypted the message and then it's checked the message to say, hey, you know, is there any
app mention or any specific keywords based on your push rules? And if that is true,
then it knows, ah, okay, I need to actually make this a red highlight rather than just a normal gray
unread count. And that's done using push rules. And push rules is stored in the count data. Final
two ones are receipts and typing. Thank you. So, hopefully, you know what receipts and typing
notifications are. The main changes for Sliding Sync is that the receipts are lazily loaded.
So, you might think, what does that mean exactly? Well, if you request a timeline limit of 10,
then you will get those 10 events. And then you will get the receipts for those 10 events,
and you won't get receipts for any other events. And you might think,
hasn't it always done this? Well, not really. So, here's some JQ for matrix HQ, which is this
RIM ID. And it's just pulling out the receipt EDU and then kind of checking, like, roughly how
many receipts there are. And you know, matrix HQ is quite a big room. So, you might think, you know,
100,000. No, there's quite a lot of rooms, quite a lot of receipts in there. And this is not great
from a bandwidth perspective, right? We don't want to be sending 53,000 read receipts, particularly
for events which you are unlikely to ever view, right? Because these could be for events that
occurred like a year ago. So, Sliding Sync also fixes that. So, with all these performance
optimizations, a very large account with 4,000 rooms can take less than a second to actually
sync, which is down from 15 minutes on Sync V2. So, very happy with that. But it's still not really
good enough. We're trying to go big or go home kind of thing. So, we want to make it even faster.
So, it is literally instant. You don't want to have to be waiting a couple of seconds. It should
just kind of open up. Just like most other messaging clients, you can just open them up and they just
work. The problem is that things are going to get a lot worse here, which I will talk about in a
moment. So, we've added in a bunch of tracing to the proxy server. So, things like, this is
runtime trace. So, you can see exactly the control flow. There's some spans there. And you can see
various optimizations that were done. So, this is identifying so bits of code. Lots and lots and
lots of commits. Sometimes it's just you forgot to add an index. Sometimes you should be doing
things in bulk instead of doing things sequentially. So, lots of work has gone into this. And also,
if you were going for 100 milliseconds, aiming for 100 milliseconds, the actual amount of
data you send is important because this starts to become quite a large factor in the total time
it takes. We can do simple things like deduplication and enabling gzip for large responses, which we
now do. And as well as that, we can aggressively cache things in memory wherever possible. So,
we don't have to query the database when clients send a request. So, there's three levels of caching
involved at the proxy level, whereas a global cache which contains kind of information which
doesn't change for any user. So, it's a constant. So, things like the number of joined users in a
room, it's the same if you're Alice or if you're Bob. It's always going to be the same. Whereas
things like the user cache or things like, what's the unread count for this room? Well,
that's going to change depending on which user. And then the connections are things like which
room subscriptions have you got or which lists, like what are your top end rooms or whatever
your sliding window is. Interesting thing to note here is that the room name is actually not
global data. The data that's used to calculate the room name is global data and is the same for
everyone, but the room name itself isn't because of DMs. So, if you have a DM with Alice and Bob,
then from Alice's point of view, the room name is Bob, but from Bob's point of view, the room name
is Alice. So, lots and lots of optimizations have been done. So, with all of this, we're going to
we're now getting less than 100 milliseconds, which is what we wanted, but it's still not good
enough because things are going to get a lot worse because clients really, it's all up to the
clients because clients want offline support and they want instant access. They don't want to have
to be having to do a network request to, when they click on a room, they want to just see the
list. They don't want to see a spinner. And in the best case, you have a spinner for half a second
maybe, and then it loads, which is, you know, it's not great, but maybe acceptable. But then if you're
on a mobile app and you go into a tunnel, then it's just going to spin it forever and then
you're sad. So, you know, users expect these things to, to kind of work instantly. And you can
kind of, you know, Sighting Sync has ways that you can kind of fix this. So, if you want to go
and instantly see the room timeline, that's fine because we can pre-cache the room timeline, right?
You can use a higher timeline limit and then you can go and pre-cache that. So, you see the
room list you click through and immediately you see, you see all the events, at least a screen's
worth of events. For the other thing, which is you want to scroll the room list instantly and
smoothly, well, you can opt out of the sliding windows entirely and you can just request really
small stub information like I just want the avatar, I just want the room name and that's it. And then
you'll know the position, the room name, the avatar, and then you can just request all the rooms
entirely. So, that will scale with the number of rooms in the user's account, but it's, it's, you
know, it's possible. And you can use something like this to see, say, timeline limit of zero,
but there's a problem here, right? Because you have a timeline limit of 20 on the first one,
then a timeline limit of zero. So, you kind of want a bit of both. So, it turns out what clients
really want is delayed data delivery. So, the API wasn't originally designed for that a year ago.
So, we've made a lot of changes to support this kind of idea of delayed data delivery. So, one
of the things is timeline trickling. So, what timeline trickling is, is that you can initially
request a set of rooms and you can say, I want only the most recent message in this room. And
then at a later point, you can say, okay, now I want the last 10 messages in this room. And then
it will go and, and effectively backpaginate those messages for you. Likewise, the clients want all
the rooms in the accounts. So, but they want maybe more detail on the rooms that are in the viewport.
So, again, you can support this by having two lists, effectively. You've got one list, which is
just the visible rooms. That might have more accurate information for, like, room previews.
So, you know, you've got room preview, you might have, you know, typing notifications,
might, you might register for typing notifications in those rooms. But then you're not really
interested in typing notifications for rooms, you know, really far down the list. And then in the
background, you can just have a separate list, which just kind of in the background goes and,
and gets all the, the other rooms and all the, the core information that you need.
So, this has kind of been a huge trade-off, right? On the one hand, you've got sync v2,
which is getting everything and is super slow, but it's got fantastic offline support as a
result of that. And on the other side, you've got sliding sync. It's super fast. You only
literally getting the data that you need, but, you know, there's compromises to be made there,
because you have to do network requests all the time and things can be slower. There's only so
fast you can do. There's only so much you can optimize a server. So, really, I think element
is kind of aiming to do something like that. So, it's mostly kind of sliding sync, but
there are compromises and trade-offs that are being made to try to give a really good offline
experience as well. So, in terms of what's next, we need to add threads, because there's no
threading support at all in sliding sync. And threads obviously only reasonably recently
landed and was, was enabled everywhere. Threads is complicated because threads are,
changes fundamental answers to questions like, is this room unread? Because normally you could
just be like, well, have you, you know, what's your red marker? What's most recent event?
Okay, it must be unread. Whereas now you could have scenarios where, you know, the most recent
event in the room is, is on a thread. So, if you were just to click on a room and you see the
timeline, they're all messages, but in a thread, you know, three days ago, there's actually a,
a newer message. So, adding support for threads is going to be quite tricky to get right. And
we'll have to probably iterate on it quite a lot, but it is coming. The other thing we're going to
be adding in is this concept called delta tokens, which, unless you've read the MSC, you'll have
no idea what it is. Ultimately, what delta tokens are is to, sliding sync has a problem
at the moment, the proxy server, because it has amnesia. So, it will time out your connection
if you don't use it for, say, half an hour. And it will clean up all that in memory state,
all those caches and things get cleaned up. And the problem is, is that then when you reconnect,
even though your client has stored those rooms and stored a lot of the timeline and stored a
bunch of room state, the proxy server doesn't know this. So, it's going to resend that information
to you. So, the point of delta tokens is to say, hey, I remember me, I've already stored, I already
know about these events. And, and then those events aren't sent to the client again in duplicate.
A few more API optimizations that we recently swapped to using lists as keys, which basically
means that instead of representing the requests and response lists as an array of lists, they're
now just a big key value map, which makes it easier because you can then reference an individual
list by the list key name. So, for things like extensions, this is great because you could
then have a way of expressing, I want typing notifications, but only on these named lists,
whereas before that was very difficult to express. And we also really want to have comprehensive
client support. It's getting reasonably stable now, and it's certainly very performant. And
Element Web uses SineSync natively in the JS SDK. But obviously, that doesn't really work for mobile.
And it would be nice to have some sort of like SDK that could be used for Android and iOS,
and maybe even web at some point. I don't think there is.
Yes. Let's talk about the Rust SDK. So, this is, sorry, overall a very technical talk. You've
already noticed that. But I'm going to lighten up a little bit more. But first about me, I'm Ben.
Hi. My name is the only name in the presentation. I don't know why. These guys have more work and
show more stuff. So, quick, yeah. I've led the Rust SDK team for the last year for Element,
and I've been working in decentralization, decentralized tech for a couple years already.
Worked at Parietech before, was leading the substrate client team there, if you know,
blockchain, that's one of the most favorite blockchain building systems. I'm going to be
working as a tech link for Active Global, where we're building on top of the Rust SDK,
a organizing app for NGOs and civil society. So, I've been working in this for over a decade.
You might know me from almost not at all threatening talk I gave at Jason, like 2017,
that was already about, like, how do you do decentralized privacy-first technology.
And now about me. Let's talk about, let me tell you a little story. We're back in 2019, 2020,
and it's the state of the clients. For the sake of argument, I'm talking about
Element clients here, because I think there's exceptions to what I'm going to tell you. But
let me tell you two truths in the line. You can tell me if you can spot the line. So,
truth number one, many clients out there don't actually implement end-to-end encryption,
which is pretty sad, because it's a very fundamental part of what we're working on.
That is mostly because it's hard. Even if you use the most widely used LibOm library,
that is a seed library, there's already slightly dated. There's, like, a lot of knowledge that
has been built up that is not easy to ingrain in this existing library anymore.
Clients usually implement the entire HTTP, or at least most of the state machine around
room, room state, who's allowed to write, as well as the entire messaging mechanics themselves,
in their own language, in their own environment. Therefore, because we have that, clients are
super fast, it is totally integrated into the system that they are, and it's just a smooth
experience. I don't have to ask you, you know, which one of this is a lie, the cake is a lie.
At this time, enter our hero. Our hero is Damir. Damir is working as a crypto dev for
Element. He's a Rust into the S, and he knows the crypto in and out. He's intending to rewrite
a plugin that he's using for an ISC client, which is called WeChat, that connects to Matrix. Because
of simple problems that are limitations in the Python implementation that WeChat offers,
he wants to rewrite it in Rust. But he doesn't really find a good place to build it on. This is
not an actual representation, but we're going to use it for now. So he goes out and says,
like, okay, let's write this. How hard could it be? He quickly realizes, like, okay, so the crypto
side with the C, I would like to have that in Rust, and I'm going to get that Y in a second.
And he pulls that out later, which is now called Votazimac. You might have heard about that, which
is our crypto implementation that we're pushing forward as live or misdiplicated. But he figures
out, like, the stuff around that to make crypto work, not the encryption itself, but the entire
thing of, like, how do I know which messages to encrypt with what key, in what room, what if a
message comes in and I don't have the encryption key? All of that state management around that is
actually as complicated and as problematic as the actual crypto. And that is why a lot of
people try to use the crypto, but then fail in doing all of that, making it a really terrible
experience, and then, like, drop it and say, like, oh, let's not do encryption. That's too hard.
But he continues and pushes on because he really wants that for WeChat and starts out with what we
know as the Rust metrics SDK. So why did he pick Rust? I'm not talking in his name, but I'm going
to give you some reasons why. If you heard about Rust before, you probably heard about it because
it's the most popular, like, most beloved language. Six years running now on the Stack Overflow
system. So who here has heard about Rust? All right. Who has used Rust? Keep your hands up.
Okay. Okay. That's fairly, fairly good. And while that is definitely true to some degree,
like, there's a lot of log for that language, it's even bigger in crypto. Because encryption,
building encryption and building that safely is really hard. At the same time, you're not,
you can't really go for Python or that kind of stuff because it's, well, too inefficient.
So most information used to you see Rust seems like a such nice alternative. So inside crypto
and encryption, Rust is already a big thing. So that's probably the main reason he chose it
because he wanted to use it. But there's also a good amount of actual reasons why Rust makes sense
to build this with. This is a screenshot of the website of Rustlang.org from yesterday.
I'm going to break it down a little more because we have to understand one key thing.
Rust was invented by Mozilla to build a new browser. They had Firefox 2010, 2011. They were
like, there's so much C, C++ in here. It's so complicated. We barely know how we can change
stuff ourselves. And it's like, it's still a Netscape code base in there, right? Like, it's like
20 years of stuff. So they were like, let's, let's build a new browser. And it's called the,
the CERBO project as a recent research project. And through that, they realized like, there's
certain things we'd like to have from new languages. And they started building their own
language to build a browser. That project still exists. It's server.org today. Mozilla has
handed off the, the management to the Linux Foundation. It's still a research project. I
recommend if you want to start with Rust. That is a really good community to start with.
But the key point here is that it, it was a language built by practitioners for practitioners.
That didn't set out to say like, hey, let's make a theoretically proven language. Let's make a really
beautiful looking language. All of these ideals were not existing. They wanted a language that
they can use that they're more efficient in building a browser with, which is already quite hard. If
you say like, I want to build a browser, that's a lot of stuff you have to do. And so they set out
to build, this is the previous claim that Rust had, which is a typesave systems language. So
systems language like level of C, C++, with zero cost abstractions.
Well, by practitioner I said that. So it's a modern language. It's, it reached 1.0 in 2015.
It is as speedy as C and C++. Sometimes speedier. The most famous example is ripgrab. If you go
for that, it's like 10 times faster than the next comparable implementation to grab over,
over a lot of files. And it does all of that without any garbage collector or VM. Again,
the goal is to have zero cost abstractions. Any abstraction that Rust gives you, and a lot of
the abstractions that the community also gives you in their own crates, has the idea of like,
we can lower that down at compile time to nothing. It doesn't actually exist. Therefore,
like garbage collector cycles, no. VM below that, no. It should work on an embedded system.
That rules out a lot of places. But all of that without memory safety bugs. Just probably the
biggest concern for any security researcher. Like buffer overflows are nonexistent effectively in
Rust. Very famously, like a couple of days ago, Google announced that since they have been shipping
Rust in Android, I think a third of the code that they ship in Android is now Rust.
Their amount of memory bugs has halved, even less than that. And that is their main concern
so far. Most of that happens at compile time. So at compile time, the compiler is a little
more annoying and telling you like, you need to tell me where this memory is going to go.
Is that in this thread or in that thread? But it also means that after it compiles, it runs.
But again, because it's built from practitioners for practitioners, it's not just about the
language. Like, you need to be able to actually work with that. That means that this is very famous
for its very good tooling. It has a really nice compiler that very famously when people jump from
other languages, and they run through the first error, they see the compiler complaining,
they switch immediately back to look at the code. In Rust, you don't do that. The compiler is
probably going to tell you what you need to change, or at least what things you need to change
to make that run. That is a completely behavioral change. The compiler is your friend telling you,
look, you need to just tell me, is that in this thread or in that thread? This is what I assume
you would want to do. It can be wrong, of course, because you have higher level abstraction that
you need to work with. But overall, it's pretty good. The same for cargo, which is the package
management system and build system, but also Rust up, which is the meta version of organizing your
own Rust installation. And all of that it provides with being built against the LLVM backend,
which means it's more or less instantly portable. When you can run it and you don't have any specific
architecture code for your Mac, it will compile for Windows as well. You basically just have to
say there's another target. The way that LLVM works, it has an abstract syntax tree of its own
in between. We compile, basically Rust compiles to that. And then everything that LLVM supports as
a target, it can compile to. And that is pretty amazing. That led to Rust being the very first
language that had native support for WebAssembly as a target language. Because it was just
switching on, oh, yeah, the target for that. At the same time, sorry, my voice isn't a little
sick, it allows you to have a C-compatible lib interface. And that makes it really nice to
embed it into other stuff and use it as a library. All right, so that's Rust. What
currently do we have in the Rust SDK now a year later? The idea is essentially that everything
you need to have to build a matrix client, it should be there. Batteries included. That specifically
means we want, we have an async type safe API. Like requests you do, they're type safe. They come
back, we check that the JSON that comes back is what it needs to be. It has a full featured
room state. So for every room that you're in, it can tell you, can you write in that room,
what kind of messages can you write, what are the other users in the room, what is their avatar,
what other states do they have, all of that stuff, it is managing for you. You don't have to
bother too much about that. It has a persistent storage layer support. So you don't have to
worry about caching it or putting it somewhere locally. You can still do that on your own if
you want. It is a pluggable interface, but it already comes with a native version which is
kind of deprecated slab, which we intend to replace with the SQLite, which is still partially there
for crypto, but not from the other side yet. But it also has, for example, support for web,
for index DB. So you can run it in the browser. One of the examples actually is an acrobot that
runs in your browser in Wasm. It's pretty awesome. And for us, almost the most important part is
that it has transparent end-to-end encryption support. When you're in a room and that room is
encrypted, it's going to send the messages out to get the keys that you need to allow you to verify
with a different device. But from the point that you join with a new device and you just say
room sent and you give it the message, it's going to send an encrypted message. That's it.
For the most part of it, unless user interaction is required, you don't have to bother about that.
It's going to store that information. It's going to make sure that when you start up the next time
through the storage support that you have all the keys there, you don't have to bother about
there being an additional end-to-end encryption that you have to take care with. I already mentioned
that it has Wasm and web support. And because of the C layer, we're also able to offer support to
different bindings out there. So we have two bindings that are used in the next generation
of element apps. You're going to see that later for Kotlin and Swift through Uni-FFI. But there's
also custom bindings for Node.js and for JS on the web as well. I think there's Python bindings
out there, but they're not maintained by us. This all allows us to go beyond what we have so far.
It allows us to ingrain more of the stuff that different clients and implementations have been
using, but that has verily cross-pollinated. If you had a really clever way of managing your
timeline in Android, the iOS people wouldn't know. That all converges into this singular place now,
and that allows us to do a lot more things a lot quicker. One of the things that we currently do
is we offer a new experimental timeline API that manages the state for you. Like back in 2018,
2019, editing messages came around and that fundamentally changed the idea of an event
in matrix. It's just not a stream of events anymore, but events acting upon other events.
This changes a message from a previous thing. With a new timeline API, you don't have to bother.
We're just going to tell you, oh, position 17. This is now this. The same is true for
reductions. The same is true for reactions. All of these things ensune threads. I don't know how
we're going to do threads yet, but that all is supposed to be right there. You don't have to
bother about the state machine changes that this requires. It's just going to tell you, hey, you
need to render a different thing now. The other thing that was mentioned before as well is support
for sliding sync. Both of these are still experimental. You have to actively switch them on
because it's interfaces that we're not confident with that are going to stick exactly the way they
are, but there's implementations out there using that. All right, so does it work? Does it live up
to the promise? Well, let's see. So in order to build sliding sync, I built a small testing UI,
and with sliding sync right now, this is a room. This is Mr. Big, my test account with, I don't
know how many rooms, but usually loading it on an element web is like a minute for initials think.
With my timeline, with sliding sync up and this testing system, it's 200 milliseconds.
It's 200 milliseconds to render the room. You can see this down here. And to pull up all other
rooms, it's like another 30 milliseconds. So yeah, it's fast. It does what it's supposed to do.
But is that actually true? I'm a core developer. Of course, the thing that I'm building here
is hopefully going to work, but how plausible is that as a SDK? Like maybe I'm just building a lot
of stuff. Okay, let's take a look at the thing itself. So the implementation on top of the Rust SDK
for this UI is a whopping 2,000 lines. It's pretty small. And most of that is actually
2e realm stuff, because actually 2e's in Rust are not that great. So you have to do a lot of
state management. The actual implementation of managing the Rust SDK is less than 130 lines
of code. Everything else you saw, including that this stores it on your hard drive, totally
abstracted away. I don't have to bother about this from that perspective. So I would say, yeah,
definitely. It does SDK. But again, so I'm a core developer. Hopefully it's easy for me to build
this. It should be fairly okay to build something as quick. But of course, it's supposed to be
working for you. All right. All right. For that, we have also brushed up our game a little bit
on documentation. And one thing I would like you to look at to check the time. It's all right.
So we have reorganized the repo a little bit to make it a little cleaner. You can see like
there's a bunch of stuff around that. There's Xtas, which is our task manager, benchmarks,
testing. That should be self-explanatory. We have the bindings and the UniFFI bind gen to
organize bindings. We have the labs, which is also where you find the jack-in implementation,
if you're curious about this. But the main stuff lives in crates and contrap is other
things built on hub. Do we have an examples folder exactly for this kind of stuff? So let me
quickly, is that possible? Roughly. I put the slides into the dev room if you want to look at them.
Quickly run through one, the SDK bot 101 thing. It allows you to directly use that from the repo
with that command. What you see on the first screen is just the imports that we need. You see
mostly Rust SDK stuff, some minor managing around that. If you're familiar with Rust,
you know that binary has this main function. We use Tokyo here. It's an async function,
right? Told you, async API. Most of that is just parsing in a very ugly way, the command line,
and then handing it over to Login and Sync. This Login and Sync sets up some minor stuff. You see
that we have a lot of information about this in code comments for right here for you. It does even
set up a slept store. You can call the Login username, you can give it a name for the bot,
that is the device that you will see, and it logs in. Going further, I don't have the time to go
through the entire thing, but it explains everything here. This bot does two things. For every
room that you ask it to join, it will automatically join, which is this first event handler,
and the second event handler is reacting on messages. An event handler in the client is
basically just a callback that you can say, like, when these kind of events come in, please tell me,
and then I react to this. Those themselves can be async again pretty nice. Then it just starts
syncing, and that's all it does, which means it's running the sync loop. This does not, at this point,
use sliding sync. As I told you, it's kind of experimental. So let's look at the room message.
So the unroom message, whenever we receive a message, we can again mention that before it's
type safe, it's going to give us the actual room message in a typed format, so we can rely on the
compiler here to make sure that things are as they should be. We make sure that we are in this room.
We try to figure out if it's a text message. If it's a text message we check for, is it
dollar bank party? If so, we're going to respond with a message, and that's all the thing does.
In reality, it looks like this. So I'm showing you this is just regular main at the moment,
and then if I run the bot, this is slightly capped so you can't see my password.
I'm here connected to that bot. You see that I'm in here. I had two more prints that are not in
main right now to make it a little cleaner. So I'm sending a message. We see that this message is
ignored, but if I send bank party, you can see it's reacting. It's sending this, and most importantly,
this is an encrypted room. I didn't have to do anything to build a bot that allows me to
live and interact with encrypted room. That's an encrypted message. I didn't have to do
anything. You saw that there was no setup. I hadn't to manage anything. The Rust SDK did all of that
for me. So if you want to learn more, if you want to use this, you can find all of the code,
of course, at metrics.metrics.rustsdk. You can join our developer and general
talking about the Rust SDK room. The example you just saw is inside the examples folder getting
started. Jack-in, the other client you saw before is in labs. Jack-in, all of that code, obviously.
I really recommend going for the getting started. It has a lot of documentation.
I also want to send honorable mention to Benjamin, who is working on Trinity, which is a
build on top of the Rust SDK, a bot framework, I would say. It allows you to write some very
small Rust that is compiled to Wasm, that it runs in the client that can react to messages.
So you can write just the message part and say, like, I have a bot that reacts to messages.
This is one. Oh, yeah. And Element is hiring. So if you are interested in working on this full-time
Element IO queries, we're going to have time for questions later. We have to get through all of
these first. So let's see what you can actually build with this. Thank you. So hello, everyone.
My name is Mauro. Honestly, my colleagues are at a slide where they presented themselves.
I don't have such a thing. So I have to be brief. I come from Italy, Naples. I'm a software engineer,
work at Element. I mostly work on the IO side of things and started working on some Rust
implementations. And, yeah, today I'm going to talk about the new client, Element X. So this
client is pretty much being built with the idea of both defined goals. The first one of them
is pretty much user experience. The thing is that we really wanted to improve over the user
experience of the current Element implementation. The thing is that Element was started as a
pretty much a showcase for what Magics was capable of. So it was a bit like an app made by
engineers for engineers. So, yeah, not everyone is into this kind of stuff. So sometimes it's a bit
hard to use for the average user and we want to improve over this. Also, we want, of course,
to have a performance to be another very important goal. Actually, just as important as UX,
we're actually, thanks to the slide in sync implementation on Element X, we're aiming to
actually launch the app in less than 100 milliseconds. That's pretty much the thing that
we're aiming for. And, of course, also optimize the bandwidth usage. Also, we want to build an app
that is reliable just from the start. So, testing code coverage is pretty much right from the start
of the project, a Niagara priority. And also, we want to build the app in a way that is actually
relying on shared components pretty much. Mattis Francis decay is just one of them,
but, of course, we're planning to build more components that will be shared across different
implementation across different platforms, different projects. So, not even necessarily
Element X, it is that we will be able to use them and, of course, anyone in the open source
community will be able to use them. So, why are we writing the Android and the iOS app?
That's actually a good question because some of these goals could actually also be achieved
with a very big refactor, but let's go more in depth on why we want to do our right. So,
let's start with Element iOS. Element iOS, it's quite old. It started in 2015. Essentially,
it was, as I said, pretty much a POC to showcase what Metrics was capable of.
It started as being named the Metrics iOS console, in fact. Then it went through a bunch of identity
crisis and changed its name three times. It was first console, then Vator, then Riot,
now it's Element. Let's hope it's going to stick with that. So, and it was built by engineers
to showcase pretty much what Metrics was capable of. But the thing is that, first of all, as I
said, the user experience was not great. Second, it was made with some very old components written
on Objective-C that used some very old architectural pattern, like MVC, which should stand for
overview controller, but in reality stands more for massive view controller because you
never find in this very, very big controller. It's just a huge mess and you start looking at
60,000 lines of code in a controller and you're like, oh my God, why am I alive? And so, yeah,
you don't want to see that anymore, pretty much. We want to move to a newer architecture.
And also, even if we did a lot of refactors on the Element iOS implementation, you essentially,
yeah, we were essentially not able to change all the old implementations since they were very hard
to maintain and we still relied on these components a lot. So, yeah, four components
are still using these old implementations. Half of the code is still in Objective-C and code
coverage is quite low. So, we decided to experiment a bit in Q2 2022. We decided to pretty much
build a minimum client using the MatrixRust SDK and pretty much the state-of-the-art frameworks
provided by Apple, like SwiftUI, but not only that, like, not so icing away and things like that.
So, yeah, and we were actually able to build this new minimum client that had a room list timeline
and it was, let's just say, a technical success. It was super fast and amazing. So, we decided to
build on top of this second POC by giving a more focus on the UX because, as I said,
yeah, now we have a performance client, but now we need to have a simple client that anyone
is able to use. So, ElementX iOS was then born. On the Android side, things are slightly different
because, technically speaking, the Android application already had a rewrite in 2019.
So, we had two choices. We could essentially just take the Android SDK,
put it on our side and pretty much replace it with the Rust SDK, that would be okay,
or maybe just rewrite it from scratch and using pretty much the state-of-the-art frameworks that
Android provides right now, like, for example, Jetpack Compose. In the end, we decided to go for the
latter for two reasons. First of all, I mean, if we're building an application on iOS that uses
the latest frameworks, why do you want to do the same for Android? And second, UX. As I said,
UX was a very, very important concern. So, even if you wanted to rebuild the app from scratch or
rewrite it, just pretty much change some stuff for the existing app, it would still require pretty
much a huge UX overall, which in the end made the rewrite even more sense.
So, pretty much, obviously, the architecture of Element Pack structured. Well, we have pretty much
the backbone of the client. It's pretty much all sitting in the Magic Trust SDK. It's all there.
And the Magic Trust SDK, through Uni-SFI, is able to expose WIFT bindings and Kotlin bindings.
It's interesting because, as pretty much Ben said, it's exposing objects that are reactive,
that the client is the only thing that it needs to care about, doesn't need to care about the events,
all the events, the newer events. It just needs to know that the event has been changed and it's
in that place. It doesn't need to know that it's a new event that came afterwards and so on. So,
the idea is that these objects at the bindings expose are actually ready to be displayed,
essentially. So, you just need to render them on the UI. And that makes the development way
wazier. And, of course, Sliding Sync is pretty much a high requirement on Element Tax, in
sense that it's being built with the idea that Sliding Sync will be pretty much the next standard
for the clients. And so, it will only work with servers that implement, for now, the Sliding Sync
proxy, essentially. So, this is an example of how the code is pretty much translated from Rust
into Zwift and Kotlin through Unify. As you can see, there is the timeline item. As I say,
it is pretty much an object that is pretty much like a view model. It's already ready to be
displayed. It just pretty much need to take the presentation data from this object and render
them on the UI. And that's it, which will make implementing clients for the future with the
Matrix Rust SDK way, way easier. So, the bindings are pretty much a separate repo. Anyone can
download them as a file, a year file for Android, or as a framework for Zwift implementations,
or you can just pretty much use a package manager like Maven Central on Android, or
Zwift package manager on, yeah, on Zwift implementations, essentially. I think it's
Zwift implementations because actually it's interesting, but the Matrix Rust SDK is scalable
of running on any Apple system target. So, I really can't wait for someone crazy enough to
build a client for Apple Watch or Apple TV. I'm pretty sure that the 10 people in the world
at the moment at Apple TV will be very pleased that there is a Matrix client on their Apple TV.
So, yeah. But, of course, ElementX is going to share more than just the Rust SDK. We're
pretty much trying to build other components that we hope to share just across ElementX,
but across multiple projects. For example, we want to be an open ID connect component,
an element call component. And, of course, since the two apps are pretty much the same up on
different platforms, they're going to share translation, they're going to share design
tokens. So, I mean, why don't we just pretty much make a component to share these elements already.
And we're actually also building an interesting component which is called Rich Text Editor,
which is essentially an SDK of written Rust that then exposes these bindings in Zwift and Kotlin
through IDFI and also in WebAssembly. And it's essentially a UI framework that you can import
into your client to render Rich Text in what you see is what you get fashion, essentially.
It's something that is going to come also into ElementX. So, keep an eye for it. But,
hey, what's this slide? Oh, actually, it's already there. Oh, but this is not ElementX.
Actually, this element, the Rich Text Editor, is already an element right now.
But in iOS, Android, and Web, you can enable it in labs. You can just go to labs,
enable it, and test it. And, you know, if you're able to break it, just, you know,
send us some feedback and we'll try to fix it as soon as possible. It's a project that I've
worked on. I'm very proud of it. I think we achieved something really great because it's a very
simple way to pretty much... It's a way in which you can create Rich Text without the need of using
markdowns and see how they look like, which will make life easier for when you create something
like this. Because I challenge everyone to make something like this with markdowns. I mean,
you would go crazy with that. So, yeah. The cool thing is that this Rich Text Editor SDK that we
built, I mean, it's not just for metrics, so, metrics client. I mean, technically speaking,
anyone could use this. Maybe you want to make a note app. You want to make, I don't know,
like an app that is your diary, whatever you want. You can pretty much implement this. And,
if you want to test it, you can scan the QR code. You will get pretty much to the
latest main implementation on Web. It's a test debug version there. The one on labs is more
stable. This one is more to play around with it. It's cool because this one, it allows you to pretty
much see how the Rich Text is transformed into a DOM representation, which is in Rust, and then
transformed back into an HTML, which is the one that we are sending over at MetricsLiance, of
course. So, of course, testing for liability, another important keyword. It's something that
we want to pretty much improve. And so, pretty much, we built a very, yeah, very stack test
infrastructure that we hope is going to cover all these areas. It's already covering most of
these areas. And, yeah, pretty much make the app more reliable, and the project way, way safer.
So, yeah, Element Tax actually has come with a lot of benefits. First of all, on the tax side,
it's way, way faster, both because the MetricsLiance SDK, I mean, it's amazing. It makes things easier
both from a development standpoint, because you just write it once and deploy it everywhere. But
at the same time, the fact that you just have your models already ready to be displayed, it's amazing.
And also, slide-in sync. And, of course, the use of declarative UIs like SwiftUI and Jetpack Compose
makes development time actually faster. And actually, also easier to test, I would say.
But also, the UI performance, also, has been improved, actually. Also, sharing components is
something that will benefit not only just Element Tax, but pretty much any client that wants to
implement a MetricsLiance. But actually, we hope that some of the sharing components that we're
building will not just benefit the Metrics community, but the overall open source community.
So, yeah, but, yeah, the major benefit, actually, we should not focus just on the main benefit that
we're offering on the tax side. We actually want to focus on the benefit we're really offering to
the users, because, in the end, the main focus of Element Tax, yeah, its performance, its tax,
its sharing components, but, of course, it's making the app more usable, more accessible,
easier to use. We want to make an app that is not just... We want to make an app that essentially
also can be used by your friends and family to chat with you, even casually during the day.
So, not just for people that essentially want to keep their conversation safe and secure for the
Metrics protocol. Rootmap. Pretty much this is the present of the future of Element Tax.
For now, you can log in, check the room list, timeline, send messages, edit, reply, react.
But there are some restrictions. First of all, of course, as I say, Sliding Sync is required,
so if your server doesn't have a Sliding Sync proxy, yeah, you can pretty much use the client
on that server. Also, it only supports authentication, and authentication, it's only through the
Metrics protocol. We want to support also OIDC and registration, but when we will build the OIDC
component, we will support that. The device verification is there, but only for emojis,
the new QR verification yet, and also no message history description. Yeah, this is pretty much
where you can find the Element X iOS version repo. There will be a public test flight coming soon,
and actually, Matthew will demo this in this afternoon. Okay, that's the plan. And regarding
Element X Android, it's a bit behind schedule because, as I said, it was developed after
Element X iOS, so it's more in a state of being set up. But of course, you can try to run it,
check the state of the repo. If you want to play around with it, this is pretty much where you
can find the actual repo of Element X Android. This is pretty much the roadmap on what we plan
to do. Actually, more than a plan, it's more like what we, let's say, it's not a deadline,
it's more like what we imagine we're able to achieve in these dates. And I was also told to be
as vague as possible, so for the release date of the public launch, I will just say that
it will come sometime in the future. Oh, all right. Okay. And that should deal with it.
So, yeah, that's all. And we can do, I think, a rapid QA session, right?
Yes, yes, we have 10 minutes. Oh, okay, nice. Rectal schedule. Nice. Oh, there's a lot of people.
Okay. Yeah, it's this around. Yeah. Please go ahead. If I remember correctly, the sliding sync
optionally element web said that you can't disable it in the warning, why is that?
So the question is, let me repeat it for the camera, why can't you disable the sliding sync
labs feature in the current version? Mostly because of N2N encrypted messages, you would
risk being unable to decrypt your N2N encrypted messages in that session. So the reason why is
because when you log into the proxy, it's going to be syncing on your account, right? And it's
going to sync forever. Well, until the access token gets invalidated, but it's going to be
syncing on your behalf. If you toggled sliding sync on then off, if you turned it off, then your
element web would be using the V2 sync as well as the proxy because the proxy didn't know you
toggled it off. So that means you've got two sync loops for your account. And that's going to cause
problems when it causes a race condition because two device messages, when they're acknowledged,
and they get acknowledged by increasing the since token, they get deleted on the server.
So if your element web was super, super fast and managed to race ahead slightly of the proxy,
then it would go and get all the two device events and the proxy would not or vice versa. And
this vice versa is the problem that is, that's trying to warn against. So if it's, if the proxy
was ahead, then you would not get a certain two device events and therefore you may potentially
lose room keys and therefore may potentially be unable to decrypt messages. Hopefully that's clear.
Do you have any data on whether sliding sync significantly impacts server load?
So the question is what about server load on sliding sync? Do we have any data?
I need clarification because do you mean at a proxy level or do you mean in like a general
general sense for native implementations of the server? Does using sliding sync improve
server performance? A native implementation, yes it would. So the, that's one of the reasons why
the existing sync implementation is slow is just because the servers have to do an awful
lot of work. And obviously I've been developing on dendrite, I know exactly what things are slow
there. So a lot of the API that's exposed to, to the clients are basically efficient ways that
you can do it. So you only get like the current state of rooms. You don't tend to need to go back
in time. You don't need to remember all your synth tokens since the beginning of time. These are
things that slow down the processing. So yes, a native implementation, but a proxy implementation
obviously is a sync loop that's going to be made. So that will increase load, right? Because that's
going to be constantly syncing on your account. Is there any plan to handle multiple accounts
in a client so you can have like an account on magic.org and have the one on your local server?
Okay, so that's an element X question, I guess. Wait, let me repeat it first. So the question is
about multi-user account support in the app. It's something that we're discussing, but for now
there is no definite plan. From the metrics SDK side, I can tell you that you can do it.
That's not an issue. So I don't, I think you were next. Saw you.
Yeah, so the question is basically how long is it going to take for sliding sync to land
and will we get native implementations in Synapse? You will get a native implementation in Synapse.
I don't know when. And yes, we're going to try to merge and land it as soon as it's practically
possible, which, you know, there's still things we need to fix, right? Like things like threading
and stuff just doesn't work. And that's actually one of the biggest blockers at the moment from us
trying out just defaulting element web to sliding sync on by default is that for compatible
servers, obviously, is the fact that we don't have threading support, so you wouldn't have feature
parity. So when we do have feature parity, then, you know, there could be element web clients
which enable it by default. It won't be in labs or be enabled in labs by default. So, you know,
we're getting there, but it's, I can't give you a time, unfortunately. Thank you. You were next.
So the question is the authentication parts in the REST SDK. So, yes, we have a login via
username and password. We have implemented OIDC in general, but I don't think it's fully tested.
And we have an SSO feature as well. So we ask the server, the specification says that, right?
The server tells us what is possible, and then we allow you to use those. So generally, yeah,
if your server is SSO, you can use the REST SDK with it. Jan here.
Question from the internet.
Ooh, a question from the internet. I heard about that.
Are there any plans or what is the status of the matrix RTC in the REST SDK?
So that the question is about RTC in the REST SDK. If you followed the RTC talk before,
you noticed that most of the RTC part of the RTC is actually offloaded to web RTC
in the current implementation. So going through a web view for us as Rust, that means we don't
have to bother about most of that. There's only some signaling that happens on the actual matrix
protocol. So we don't have at the moment the plan to implement an actual RTC
our side. I wouldn't see where you would want to do that for other than that view.
So currently it's not on the boat map, at least for our side.
Yeah. So that's a common one as Rust is very, so the question is about IoT devices.
Could you do that with Rust? I see you can. Yes. That is generally possible. We have,
because of the storage systems and some other things in there, and because
matrix itself is still quite heavy as an overall protocol.
We have tried to get it into an actual embedded device. That is not at the moment possible.
We would have to improve a lot on the way that we use Rust. Rust itself provides that, but we
can't do that. But you can use it, for example, on an Android, not an Androidino, but a Raspberry Pi.
We know of people that run Raspberry Pis that have signals coming in and then they use the
Rust SDK to send it over into rooms. That is definitely possible, because it's more or less
just a bot, right? From our perspective, it's just a bot. So that is possible, but you still need
significant amount of memory at the moment, and that would make it not possible for actual
embedded devices yet. If anybody wants to do that, come to me. I can show you and mentor you
and help you, because it would be very exciting if we had possible to do that. Yan, another question
from the internet? There's also a question about the element X. What you see is what you get,
Editor, is it still possible to use just markdown if you want to just use knockdown?
So the question is about the element X. With your big editor, can you still use markdown
if you want to use markdown? Yeah, actually, even on the current element implementation
that is on the on the client, you can actually also still use markdown. So there's an option
that allows you to turn off the rich text and turn back the simple text. And when the simple text
is on, pretty much you can use markdowns. But when it renders in what you see, what you get fashion?
So the question is about does the markdown then render in the WYSIWYG?
No, when you're using the simple text version, it's rendering pretty much like a simple text
with the markdowns. Or naming it in the rich text with also the markdowns. Currently not,
we're pretty much trying to build the rich text editor as it is with just the rich text
using the formatting toolbar to be the most performant and good and in simple tools as possible.
But it is something that for sure, when we have a very stable product, we will work into, we'll
look into. Another question for me? Will this finally unite the markdown syntaxes that you
can use in different element clients? Will that finally reduce the amount of different
markdown syntaxes that you can use in element clients?
And I'm sure about the question actually.
Okay, will the WYSIWYG editor in simple text mode use one unified markdown implementation
so you don't have to remember different variants of markdown and different clients?
But you're talking if we are going in the future to support the markdowns inside the WYSIWYG
directly without turning off the rich text? This is what you mean?
I think there's a confusion here. You switch on the WYSIWYG editor, then you get the WYSIWYG.
If you turn it off, you have a simple text mode that is some, you can do some markdown,
but it's not going to be rendered inside of this. So it's just going to fall back to the existing,
right? It's going to fall back to the existing implementation. So therefore, yeah, to answer
your question, it's falling back to the existing implementation. So no, they will still be incompatible.
So that we might switch to use the markdown for round tripping, because at some point,
I think this was the previous question, that people are going to want to round trip between
the markdown implementation and the WYSIWYG one. And to do that consistently, you're going to want
to use the same library. You put that in the Rust layer. And finally, we get out to the nightmare
of Common Mark versus GitHub, Flavid, Markdown, versus whatever random library is the different
element platforms have. I think Android is still out of sync with the others.
One last question. Where can we meet you today, or maybe later, if we have more questions?
I think we're going to hang around here, right? Yeah, for sure. We'll be able to stand soon.
We have a stand in K1. I'm just going to be around here lurking, so just talk to me.
Yeah, same for me. I'm going to be here. I'm the guy with that hat. All right. Thank you very much.