Wednesday, when we did the unboxing event, that since we do hope that everyone will be
welcomed to a Penpot project, we needed to make sure that the invite system could cope
with all the different use cases that you get with that link expiration, who got the
invite, do any tree send it, etc., etc.
Otherwise, the onboarding experience would be tough and people would not be joining the
design project.
And this is very important for us because this is not only a tool for designers to just
express their creativity, but also for developers to join the design process to be welcomed there.
So this is very important for us.
But of course, we had many improvements in the interactive prototype feature.
This is just one example for the overlay advancement.
So here you can see how a design asset is being self-referred and you get a very nice
pixel-perfect overlay on a button and then an animation that comes with a mouse click.
Right?
Do you like this?
I think you do.
Yeah, I think you do.
This is happening.
This is...
This is amazing.
So this is just about a token.
I do mean, I mean, do go and enjoy Penpot, but it has many, many features on advanced prototyping,
but this is one thing that actually came from this official release.
As it did nested boards, so here you can see in this animation like an independent board
being dragged to another board and having this nesting effect.
This actually was a bit tricky because as you know, Penpot uses SVG like natively.
So when I say open standards, we do really mean open standards.
And it was tough to have this root element having everything, so to have different independent
components being designed, we had to do this nested board trick, but that trick actually
gave us a lot of potential because when you have nested boards, you can do much more advanced
compositing in general, and so we have like the best of world worlds.
We have SVG, but also these neat tricks for compositing.
Also let me remind you, for those of you that don't know much about Penpot, that we have
like some innovations in terms of where to find stuff.
When you do engineering, you think about scale, like I need to scale up.
I need to automate.
I need to have everything like in tiny bits so I can combine them any way I want.
With design, with big design architectures, you have that same challenge, otherwise it
gets just manual, like design is just manual, and it can only go as far as your brain can
cope with stuff.
So having like your components, your libraries and assets readily available here, whether
there are fonts or colors or design tokens or whatever, it's really cool.
Also a whole lot of libraries, and you drag and drop, or you create new ones, and they
are there on your left pane.
So this actually comes from the Penpot design system, which is the first one example that
you can one-click import.
If you go to Penpot, you do the onboarding, it's very nice, by the way it's a nice bottle
challenge that you can try and do.
Anyone here did the bottle challenge?
Some of you do, it's a nice little game where you learn by fun, like it's like you learn
the Penpot basics using this bottle challenge.
But when you actually go into more advanced topics, this is what you really need.
So go and check the Penpot design system because it's kind of neatly organized.
And then we get something so cool that no one had, which is FlexLayout.
So every design and prototyping system out there would have this killer feature where
you can smartly apply rules to your design.
Say I want my design to flow this way and then you would change the content within that
design and those rules would apply automatically.
So for designers, I'm seeing people are saying yes, yes, I know why we're talking here.
Some designers would feel a massive productivity boost thanks to that.
You can call it auto layout, smart layout, fancy layout, whatever.
They could not have this once they were exposed to that.
It's like not having this once you know about this intelligent layout system is like going
really back in time and having to do everything manually.
So the problem with this as we thought at Penpot was that unfortunately these layout
systems were design-centric, which is not bad per se, but was not developer-friendly.
Basically it was not team-friendly, meaning designers would do their smart layout system
and then all the vocabulary and the ideas, the abstractions were just for the designers
to understand and to enjoy and then developers would go there and say I need to translate
this into code.
Let's hope there's no issues, by the way, issues.
Not only technical issues but also friction issues like back and forth.
This am I in control?
No, I'm not.
Neither the designer nor the developer.
They would feel like they would have to constantly double-check and you don't scale up your design
or your code if you have to do that.
Penpot came with a completely different approach and said what if we have code first design
layout?
What if already the design is the code?
You can do a ton of stuff with Flex CSS.
It's actually quite advanced.
So what if we say let's do a developer first design layout system and we came up with Flex
layout and please do a plot here because it's the first ever tool to have this and it's
open source.
The great thing about this is that this is not a gift from engineers to designers saying
I made this for you, please use it.
I hope you're excited about this but actually designers wanted this.
So no compromises, everyone wins.
We got 50 to 60 volunteers for the better testing of this.
I'm not saying you could not test it using our development branch but like the proper
environment setup for people to go and do some simple tests like this one and give us
feedback and the feedback was phenomenal.
I think 80% came from designers and 20% from engineers.
So that was nice.
Given the fact that in the world so that you know it statistically there's one designer
pretend developers roughly.
We don't think that's a good ratio.
At colleagues we have one to two so pretty different.
Somewhere in between perhaps one to four would be great but of course to better test this
we couldn't have the one to ten ratio in our poll.
We needed to reverse that.
But we didn't have to work hard to achieve that because designers were actually asking
to better test this in the first place.
So if you're familiar with flex CSS you can see properties there and then of course you
get I'm here I'm simulating to this is a real time collaboration because we do have real
time collaboration of course and this is like two browsers.
It doesn't look like that because I made it like fix a perfect in a way but that code
pane there the coding spec is actually a second browser just just beneath right nothing fancy
but you can see how real time that is changing.
So a designer is changing the design using flex layout and as the designer does that
the developer can see that code being changed just is a different tab selection there that's
that's all it takes.
So I'm not saying that a developer should like be like quickly copy and pasting when
it changes but it's nice for for the demo now you see that it's real there's no like
export concept of anything and really that's it thank you it happened I do hope we have
some time for question because I planned for that that is great over the whole point okay
I'd rather not pick if you could you could store that but not yeah and is there any kind
of process I can follow to do we have something that exists to guide me so the question was
about perhaps migrating the design system from you could you could so if you're using
a design system on Figma right now and you want also to use pen pod there's a ton of
overlap so it might feel weird for you to use the two if not you're not migrating the answer
is I'm not sure it makes sense because it is about team dynamics this is about people
collaborating so unless you want to export these Figma assets and use it like privately
for you with no going back if that is I mean you're smiling so I guess that that's what
I want I want to live in my private open source world okay but that that seems to me I get
I get that you you can save some money doing that but honestly it's going to not save you
much time so you have to keep a balance there because it's going to be back and forth not
within pen pod but within two tools that compete in the space of the use case but I mean go
ahead and tell me how it looks perhaps I'm mistaken but I think it's going to have a
bit of overhead for you if you're willing to take that you have a sticker you I'll give
you a sticker like the shiny one you know okay by the way who was my ask a question
who was here three years ago can you raise your hand okay yeah okay we have stickers
like super premium stickers for you I so my question is you showed us there was a live
update of this yes so the question is we saw the real time transformation between the
design and the code is it full duplex can I change the code not for now not for now
but of course I mean it feels like you would like to do the other way around I'll actually
go on with that question theme and say what if you connect that with a gear repository
and you change that in the gear repository that comes back and changes the design what
if as a designer you change something that also goes to the gear repository and triggers
a CICD process ah okay so we thought about that because it's kind of what comes next
obviously but yeah so good question we've got to cover it okay thank you
so resources for helping teams migrating from other tools to Penpot yeah yeah I mean
Figma what is that Figma owns 80% of the market for designers 80% Adobe now owns 87% of the
market thanks to that so obviously yeah I get that we have a plug-in an expert plug-in
it's we hope that the community can help us just improve it so that you can basically
export all that from we actually don't know how much time we've got for that plug-in to
be okay for Figma but it's still there so that is one way you can quickly test that
it's not any means complete so it will give you like the basics but it might be enough
and then I think everything like exporting stuff and just uh re-importing that is really
quick for teams to have the design system re-uploaded here somehow I don't think it's
going to take much time if you have the motivation it's just you know some I mean depending on
the complexity of the prototypes and design this is for prototyping and this is also for
design so depending on the quality for each topic it might get but yeah the export plug-in
we really hope that we get more help from the contribution from the community so if
anyone here is interested in like those like serialization challenges for the SVG and the
JSON because it's all it has really that would be great from the abstraction model
that we have from Figma to actually proper you know open standards fine so yeah those
um good um thank you
I'm curious about the business side things you mentioned Figma and how do you plan to
continue to Figma and be successful at it and at the same time drive your business forward?
So Kaleidos is a company um actually the original title is Kaleidos's open source that's the
SL because we're a Spanish company um so the idea for us is to make sure that we follow
this um we think it's going to be uh kind of an enterprise edition that will give companies
things that the power user does not want or doesn't need we call that privately publicly
tax the controller okay so that is uh something that we don't really need right now because
to be honest there's still a ton of things that we have to do for the product but basically
uh perhaps in two years if we are relevant we hope we are relevant we'll see uh see you
in two years force them you know but uh if we are really relevant then uh we will look
for those tax the controller uh features that big companies are fine uh they won't contribute
with code they won't contribute with content they will contribute with money right so we
don't have like the details but it's going to be like and this has been publicly said
many times the power user gets open source forever is the companies wanting to have this
control mechanism that will have to pay for something that is exclusive to them whether
it's self-host or SaaS we don't care actually by the way there is also a desktop app by
the community um that encapsulated Penpot with Electron so you can also have the pure
desktop native you know experience um so yeah um it's it's there actually in the community
space community.Penpot.app we elaborate a bit more on that but yeah the only way this
will be sustainable is a company is that we are really relevant um surprisingly the the
design space in our view is quite immature like you have one tool you know winner takes
all then the next tool then the next there are subsequent winners uh we hope that we
add fragmentation to that uh but still uh and so be be be relevant so we have like
one minute left if you the answer a question you answer the second part and this is the
first part of the hug actually you tend to compete with Figma you tend to maybe drive
business away from Figma toward Penpot. Well I think uh will we the the playbook that we
have is quite unique and unprecedented like this is open source design and prototyping tool
so we hope that we have a bottom-up uh distribution model like people are really saying this is
actually much better and uh we are hoping this is this is part of our yeah this is hope that you
remember that ratio one designer pretend developers that developers actually loving open source
do bring um Penpot to the forefront without the help from open source developers I'm sure this
is not going to happen not because design open designers don't like open source just because
the the economics of that will take much longer um so yeah that one to ten ratio is the only
what is the only time I would I'm happy with that ratio like in this particular case it's like
so we are counting on open source developers today. Okay if you want to have a chat afterwards
and I'm sure Pablo is very very happy to answer questions so that's we have five minutes for
people to leave and people to come in so I'm going to say thank you Pablo. Thank you.